<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The conquest of temptations, or Mans victory over Satan especially, the great assaults, at the agony of death, full of very strong and effectuall consolations, to sustaine and comfort the weakest heart, in the greatest conflicts which can befall a Christian in the vvhole course of of life, and approach of death / gathered by the holy and deuout labour of Iohn Gerard, doctor of diuinitie, and superintendent of Heldburge ; newly Englished by Rich. Bruch, minister of Gods word.</title>
            <author>Gerhard, Johann, 1582-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11767.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S5215</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">39960674</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 39960674</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72164)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1946:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The conquest of temptations, or Mans victory over Satan especially, the great assaults, at the agony of death, full of very strong and effectuall consolations, to sustaine and comfort the weakest heart, in the greatest conflicts which can befall a Christian in the vvhole course of of life, and approach of death / gathered by the holy and deuout labour of Iohn Gerard, doctor of diuinitie, and superintendent of Heldburge ; newly Englished by Rich. Bruch, minister of Gods word.</title>
                  <author>Gerhard, Johann, 1582-1637.</author>
                  <author>Bruch, Richard, minister of Gods word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 121, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.S. for Roger Iackson, and to be solde in Fleetstreet neere the great Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, tightly bound, and with print show-through; some loss of text. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A(-A₁)-F¹² (last 2 leaves blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Temptation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devil --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONQVEST of Temptations: <hi>OR</hi> Mans victory ouer Satan, Eſpecially, the great Aſſaults, at the Agony of DEATH.</p>
            <p>Full of very ſtrong and effectuall Conſolations, to ſuſtaine and comfort <hi>the weakeſt heart, in the greateſt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts which can befall a Chriſtian in the whole courſe of Life, and approach of Death.</p>
            <p>Gathered by the holy and deuout labour of IOHN GERARD, <hi>Doctor of Diuinitie, and Super</hi>-intendent of Heldburge.</p>
            <p>Newly Engliſhed by <hi>Rich. Bruch,</hi> Miniſter of GODS Word.</p>
            <q>
               <l>He that dyeth before he dye,</l>
               <l>Shall not dye when he doth dye.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Roger Iackson,</hi> and to be ſolde in Fleetſtreet neere the great Conduit. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST RELIGIOVS AND worthy KNIGHT, Sir <hi>Thomas Vauaſur,</hi> Knight-Marſhall: and to the moſt pious and well-affected Lady his Wife, the Lady <hi>Mary Vauaſur.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>R. B.</hi> wiſheth here on Earth the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and in Heauen the comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all happineſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince it is in mans life,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> as it is in an Enterlude, that it skils not how long, but how well it be acted, and that the word of truth giues out this for a truth,<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.10.</note> the end of a thing is better then the beginning; it concernes all men to ſtriue to make good that which they cannot make long, and hauing begunne well, to
<pb facs="tcp:150476:3"/> perſeuere ſo doing, leſt they leeſe the things that they haue wrought,<note place="margin">2 Iohn. v. 8 Heb. 3.14.</note> if they keepe not ſure vnto the end, the beginning, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are vpholden. Surely, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our yeeres is knowen to GOD alone, our dayes are in his hand; this only remaines vnto vs, while wee are in this world, to keepe our ſelues vnſpotted of the world,<note place="margin">Pſa. 119.1 Iob. 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>immaculati in viâ,</hi> vpright &amp; vndefiled in the way, holding on our way with the righteous, and with the pure of hands, increaſing our ſtrength. Which that we ſhould not doe, the old enemie of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, full of all ſubtiltie and malice, doth by all meanes labour ſtill to hinder; who, though he be very buſie with vs to auert vs from the good, and to make vs forſake our owne mercies in the whole courſe of our liues, yet he doth eſpecially <hi>inſidiari calcaneo,</hi> trip at the heele, lay wait at the end, to make vs then let goe the holde that we haue, and the hope of aſſurance, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cannot before hand make vs to deny the faith, and make ſhipwracke of good conſcience:<note place="margin">Eph. 6.13.</note> whom that we may not onely know how to reſiſt, but alſo reſiſting to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome in the euill day, and finiſhing all things to ſtand faſt, whoſe fiery darts that wee may quench, this little Booke
<pb facs="tcp:150476:3"/> giues vs both the ſhield of faith, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall armour, in which kinde though I haue read and ſeene others writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, yet neuer did I peruſe any done ſo full and ſo feelingly, ſo ſuccinct in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in ſo good order and method. This when I had firſt turned into our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, being thereunto requeſted: in the next place, when I thought to whom I might beſt offer it, your Worthineſſe (moſt religious Knight and Lady) came into my minde, perſons as in your ranke and place eminent, ſo much more eminent in your vertues, who in the example of your zeale in Religion, and loue of the truth, your pietie and charitie, your meekeneſſe and affabilitie are a patterne vnto others, and doe in the integritie of your liues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of good workes,<note place="margin">Lib. de conuer. a ſeculo, ad <hi>Theo. Sen.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>multum militare acquiſitionibus Chriſti,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentius,</hi> Purchaſe much for Chriſt, and purchaſe to your ſelues in the world, with the teſtimony of a good conſcience, that feaſts your ſoules continually, the ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of a good name;<note place="margin">Pro. 15.15</note> which two things are better vnto you then all riches. Wee that are of your neighbourhood know and ſee the care that you haue of religious duties, and the workes of charitie which
<pb facs="tcp:150476:4"/> you doe; your lowlineſſe in your wealth and Honour, and other your remarkeable vertues: It remaines onely, that you that haue ſo well begunne, and hitherto ſo well continued, doe now ſtriue to perſeuere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end, that you may receiue a full reward, that you may crowne the good that hath gone before in you with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, and that ouercomming the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties that are yet behinde, you may at laſt bring your ſhip to the Hauen where you would be: Which that you may the better doe, you ſhall finde no ſmall helpe and furtherance in this ſmal Booke, which euery where breathing Conſolations, will arme your ſoules againſt all Temptations, and againſt the time of your diſſolution come ſo compoſe your ſoules to Death, that you ſhall ſleepe ſweetly in the Lord, in the peace of a good Conſcience, in ſure and certaine hope of eternall life: vnto which the Lord of his mercy giue you an entry with all Saints, through his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, our Lord and Sauiour. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips humbly deuoted and wiſhing your beſt good R. Br.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:4"/>
            <head>To the very Reuerend and famous men, excelling in Pietie, Learning and Authoritie: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IOHN SCHRODER, a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Diuine, and moſt worthy <hi>Miniſter, appointed of the Church of</hi> Norinberg. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. MARTIN GVNGE, the moſt deſeruing Preacher of the Court <hi>of</hi> Saxo-Coburg. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IOHN ALDENBVRG, his <hi>moſt faithfull fellow Miniſter of the Church of</hi> Coburg: <hi>His Maſters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plato in Phaedone. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>friends and Brethren in Chriſt, ſingularly beloued.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any man (Reuerend and moſt famous men, my Maſters Friends &amp; Brethren in Chriſt to be had in ſingular honour) would accommodate that ſame Platonicall definition of Philoſophie, that it is a Meditation of death, to the true Theoſophie of Chriſtians, hee may doe it,
<pb facs="tcp:150476:5"/> as I thinke, with the good leaue of the truth, ſeeing as it were the beginning and end thereof, doth conſiſt in the Meditation of death. Now I vnderſtand vnder the name of death, both the death of Chriſt, and our death alſo. The death of Chriſt and his Paſſion, is the waight of the Chriſtian name,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.2.</note> thence the Apoſtle did iudge, that hee knew no other thing among the Corinthians, then Chriſt crucified and dead. By the death of Chriſt was made an expiation of our ſinnes, a deſtruction of the power of Satan, a confirmation of the new couenant, and an eaſing of the terrours, which are wont to be preſent in our death: therfore the Meditation of the death of Chriſt ought neuer to depart from our memorie. Neither let vs any time of our life forget our owne death, that as Death expects vs euery day, ſo wee may alſo expect that againe each day.<note place="margin">Hieron. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt ad Pauli.</note> He which remembers daily that hee ſhall die, he doth eaſily contemne all earthly things, he prepares himſelfe by true and earneſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion to a bleſſed death: he giues his minde to ſincere pietie: he doth patiently endure all manner of aduerſitie, and is ſet on fire euen from the heart, with an ardent deſire of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.<note place="margin">Pſa. 90.12.</note> Teach vs, O Lord, prayes <hi>Moſes,</hi> to number our dayes, that wee may apply our hearts vnto wiſedome: therefore a great part of Chriſtian wiſedome conſiſts in the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Meditation of death. That muſt a long time be learned, which that it may once right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be done, ſtands vpon our eternall ſaluation. It is appointed for all men once to dye: but to dye godlily, to dye in Chriſt, to dye bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly befalls not all men; therefore our minde
<pb facs="tcp:150476:5"/> muſt be prepared to that bleſſed good diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of dying, yea it muſt be garded with the ſhield of the Word and Prayers. For if at any, ſurely in that laſt time of our life, the enemie that hath a thouſand wiles, doth lay a ſnare for our ſaluation, and endeauours with all his ſtrength to wreſt the poſſeſſion thereof from vs, whether ſome of the auncients doe apply it, that the infernall Serpent is ſaid eſpecially to bite the heele, for he knowes very well, I ſay he knowes, that all the matter is in ſafety if that laſt conflict be valiantly ouercome of vs: on the other ſide that it will be ioyned with our euerlaſting reproach and loſſe, if the other parts of our life, as it were of a Comedie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well acted, wee behaue our ſelues not ſo comelily &amp; valiantly in this laſt Cataſtrophe. Hence come thoſe diuers tentations, with which as it were with Rammes, he aſſaults our hearts in diſeaſes, and in the agonie of death: hence come thoſe fierie Darts, which he caſts againſt vs with all his ſtrength: hence comes that horrour and anguiſh, which wee feele when wee are ſet before the gates of Death. Bleſſed is hee, which ſhall heere ouercome, bleſſed is he which ſhall be faithfull to death,<note place="margin">Apoc. 2.3.</note> hee ſhall be made partaker of all thoſe good things which are promiſed to the ſtout Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of Chriſt in the Reuelation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>What is our life? t'is Death we doe deface,</l>
               <l>Our age by dying, life and death doe pace</l>
               <l>Hand ioyn'd in hand. But Chriſt the Captaine is,</l>
               <l>And gate of life; our death is ſlaine by his.</l>
               <l>He that doth firmely truſt in him ſhall bee</l>
               <l>From wound of death eternall ſafe and free.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:150476:6"/>
               <l>But this our hope with diuers ſtormes is toſt,</l>
               <l>When in Deaths agonie we are neere loſt.</l>
               <l>To ouercome theſe ſtormes will moſt auaile vs,</l>
               <l>Leaſt life in lifes firſt entry chance to faile vs.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wherefore whereas I haue endeauoured by ſuch an explication of the Hiſtorie of the Paſſion and death of Chriſt as I could make, which I did ſet forth of late, to inſtill into god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindes the Meditation of the death of Chriſt, I haue thought that I ſhall do a worke worth the labour, if I propoſe vnto them alſo the Meditation of our death. To which end I haue written this Manuell of Conſolations to be oppoſed to the terrours of death, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in the agonie of death, for mine owne priuate vſe onely, for I carrie about a ſickly bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, a weake veſſell. Moreouer, Death now of late hath made a very lamentable ſlaughter in my houſe, and there are ſome cauſes for which it is feared, that I ſhall not liue long; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would prepare and arme my minde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to this laſt battell; and hemmed in as I am with ſo many domeſtique euils, I beſtowed ſome dayes on the godly Meditation of this Booke, which Meditations of mine, ſuch as they are, ſeeing (perhaps) they may alſo be profitable to others, I haue not gaine-ſayed that they ſhould be made common: But this I would haue men admoniſhed in the very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of this writing, that I haue not written theſe things to ſecure impenitent and hard hearts, but to the contrite, broken, and weake conſciences. Exhortations to true pietie haue another place; this whole labour is imployed in conſolations to be oppoſed to death, and
<pb facs="tcp:150476:6"/> temptations in death. Whoſoeuer therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to receiue this oyle of Conſolations, let him bring the veſſell of a contrite heart. For what is conſolation vnto him, which is not yet contrite, broken, or made ſad? But to you men very Reuerend and moſt famous, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Friends, and Brethren in Chriſt, ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly beloued, I would entitle this Manuell, that there might be extant a publique teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of that moſt ſtraight friendſhip and brotherhood which hitherto we haue obſerued betweene our ſelues one to another: ſeeing that of all, and amongſt all, I eſteeme you dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in this world, as of whoſe pietie, curteſie, faithfulneſſe, and other many vertues I haue had plentifull experience in our fiue yeeres con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. You alſo carrie about you a ſickly body, neither can it chuſe but that the memory of Death ſhould daily come into your minds. Therefore I doe not doubt, although your faith doth not want thoſe props which I haue gathered together in this little Booke for mine owne, and other mens vſe; yet that the reading thereof will not be vnpleaſant vnto you. Eſpecially ſeeing whatſoeuer is in it, it doth proceede from a friendly &amp; well-affected minde. The Lord Ieſus with his grace, and with his ſpirit euery way bleſſe vs, and the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of our Miniſterie. Giuen at <hi>Coburg</hi> the Kalends of May. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1611.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RR. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. DD. Studioſiſſ. I. G. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:7"/>
            <head>THE TABLE of Temptations.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> THe fore-runners of death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The three-forked Mace of death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The vexation of ſinne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> The memory of Actuall ſinne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> The doubting of the application of the benefites of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> The falſe perſwaſion of faith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Inſufficient griefe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> The waight of griefe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> Deſperation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> Blaſphemie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> The particularity of the promiſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> The abſolute decree of reprobation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> The application of the merit of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> The want of the euidence of the words.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> Falling out of the couenant of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> Vncertaine taking into the couenant of Baptiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> The vnworthy vſe of the holy Supper.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> The weakeneſſe of faith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> The want of the feeling of faith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> The want of power to beleeue.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> The ſmall number of good workes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> The want of merits.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23</hi> The accuſation of the Law.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150476:8"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>24</hi> The accuſation of conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25</hi> Too late repentance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26</hi> Doubting of the grace of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27</hi> Defect of due preparation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28</hi> The doubting of the inhabitation of the holy Spirit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29</hi> The doubting of perſeuerance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30</hi> The ſnares and ſtrength of Satan.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31</hi> The Apoſtaſie of many.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32</hi> Doubting of the writing into the Book of life.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33</hi> The feare of Death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>34</hi> The ſting of death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35</hi> The ſorrowes of death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>36</hi> Too timely death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37</hi> Seruices farther due to the Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>38</hi> Our life abridged by our owne default.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>39</hi> The loue of this life.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>40</hi> Separation from Wife, Children, and kinsfolke.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>41</hi> The ſtopping vp of the eares in death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>42</hi> The apparent inutilitie of the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>43</hi> The horrour of the duſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>44</hi> The abſurdity of the reſurrection.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>45</hi> The flames of Purgatorie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>46</hi> The rigour of the laſt iudgement.</item>
               <item>In concluſion is added a prayer in ſicknes.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150476:8"/>
            <head>Conſolations, to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to all Temptations in generall, but more ſpecially <hi>to Death, and to the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> in the agony of Death.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> The fore-runners of Death.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Diſeaſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.9.</note> the vſher and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of death, hath oppreſſed mee: I haue receiued the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death in my ſelfe. I ſee that I muſt leaue this life; then which nothing is more ſweet; I muſt leaue this world; then which nothing is more pleaſant, I muſt leaue this houſe of my body; then which nothing is more deare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>THou wert created of God, not for this wretched and momentany,<note place="margin">Sap. 2.23.</note> but for a bleſſed and eternall life: for God framed the firſt Parent of our kinde in corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150476:9"/> to immortalitie: neither wert thou redéemed of Ieſus Chriſt for this fraile and miſerable, but for that perpetuall and moſt happy life, which is to be expected in the heauens, ſeeing it is a certaine and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitate ſaying,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15.</note> that Ieſus Chriſt came into the world, that he might ſaue ſinners: neither wert thou called of the holy Ghoſt, through the word, to the kingdome of Chriſt for the moſt ſhort vſe of this light, but that hereafter thou mighteſt paſſe out of the kingdome of grace into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory, out of the Church militant to the Church triumphant, out of the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of teares into the field of ioyes: for if in this life only we beléeue &amp; hope on Chriſt, wee are the moſt miſerable of all men.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19.</note> Wherefore, when thou ſéeſt that thou art to be led through the gate of death to that life, for which thou wert created of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for which thou wert redéemed of the Sonne, for which liues ſake thou wert ſanctified of the Spirit, doe not (I pray thée) deſpiſe the friendly counſell of God againſt thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">Luke 7.30.</note> but moſt readily obay and follow God that calls thée.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Of the three-forked Mace of death.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The tempted.</head>
                  <p>THe thought of death doth terrifie mee, the terrible ſhape of that enemy doth vexe my ſoule;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55.</note> hee ſhewes mee his ſting, which is ſinne; he threatens mee with his cruell three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forked Mace, while he caſts before mine eyes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150476:9"/> and my heart the wrath of God; the accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Law,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23</note> and the hainouſneſſe of my ſinnes: ſeeing death is the wages of ſinne, and through ſinne death hath entred into mee,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.18.</note> as it hath done alſo into the whole world.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>BVt I admoniſh thée, that being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and from the bottome of thy heart contrite, for the ſinnes that thou haſt committed, thou behold him, which was dead for thée on the Altar of the Croſſe, that thou mighteſt not be ſubiect to eternal death. Turne thine eyes away from the outward ſhape of death, and turne them to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.15.</note> which by his death hath deſtroyed him which had the power of death, that is the Deuill; and hath deliuered vs which through the feare of death were all our life ſubiect to bondage:<note place="margin">Hoſe. 13.14. Ioh. 11.25.</note> hee is death to our death: he is a ſting to that Hell which wée haue deſerued: he is the reſurrection, and the life, he that beléeueth on him,<note place="margin">verſ. 26.</note> although he were dead, yet hee ſhall liue, and euery one that liueth and beléeueth in him,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.22.</note> ſhall not dye for euer. Therefore as in <hi>Adam,</hi> that is, for ſinne deriued out of <hi>Adam</hi> into vs, and for actual ſinnes heaped vpon this, all of vs are ſubiect vnto death, and are conſtrained, at the laſt, to dye: ſo alſo in Chriſt, the Captaine of life, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour of death, wee are all quickened by faith, that which alſo, our Captaine of life confirmeth with a graue and ſerious oath: <hi>Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 5.24.</note> 
                     <hi>hee which heareth my word, and beleeueth on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150476:10"/> him that ſent mee, hath eternall life, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not into iudgement, but hath paſſed from death to life,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.51.</note> And againe, <hi>Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you, If any man ſhall keepe my word, hee ſhall not ſee death for euer.</hi> Beléeue Chriſt therfore,<note place="margin">Iohn 14.6.</note> which is the truth: beléeue him promiſing, beléeue him ſwearing: Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and Earth ſhall paſſe away,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.33</note> but the words of Chriſt ſhall not paſſe away.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> The vexation of Sinne.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>THE remembrance of my ſinnes doth come into my minde; for I was not onely begotten,<note place="margin">Pſa. 51.7.</note> conceiued, and borne in ſinne, but I haue increaſed this ſumme of originall and hereditary debt, with diuers debts of manifold and moſt grieuous ſinnes, through the courſe of my whole life: how therefore can I hope that God will be fauourable vnto me, whom I haue ſo often offended? How can I perceiue any comfort in death, ſeeing death is the wages due to my ſinnes, and to thoſe that are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, the beginning of the ſecond and eternall death?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>BEhold Chriſt hanging on the altar of the Croſſe, and powring out for thy ſinnes the price of thy redemption, that is, his precious bloud.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.8.</note> The bloud of Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, doth cleanſe thée from all ſinnes:<note place="margin">2 Ioh. 2.2.</note> he is the propitiation for thy ſinnes, and for the ſinnes of the whole world: for neither came he into the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150476:10"/> world for that end that he would be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto, but that he might miniſter to others, and giue his ſoule a redemption and price for the ſinnes of many. And leſt there ſhould ariſe or remaine any doubt in thée of this matter: therefore from heauen which is the Throne of truth, by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, which is a Spirit of truth, that name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> moſt ſwéet, and moſt full of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation was brought, and giuen to this our Mediatour before he was conceiued in the wombe; and what other thing is Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus then a Sauiour?<note place="margin">Luk. 2.31.</note> for therefore this name was giuen to Chriſt, becauſe hee ſaues his people from their ſinnes.<note place="margin">Mat. 1.21.</note> This is that Lambe of God, which takes away the ſinnes of the world.<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29.</note> This is that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which therefore came into the world, that he might ſaue ſinners. This is the high Prieſt of the new Teſtament,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15. Epheſ. 5.2.</note> which hath deliuered himſelfe for our ſins to be an offering and a ſacrifice of a ſwéet ſmelling ſauour vnto God. It is Chriſt, which hath powred out his owne bloud for the remiſſion of ſinnes:<note place="margin">Mat. 26.28 1 Pet. 2.24</note> which hath borne our ſinnes in his body on the wood: which was wounded for our iniquities, and was broken for our ſinnes:<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.5.</note> God hath laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and as it were, by a troupe made he hath made to fall vpon him the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of vs all: Him that hath not knowne ſinne, God hath made ſinne for vs; <hi>that is,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.21</note> he hath imputed our ſinnes to him, he hath layd vpon him the puniſhment of our ſins, he hath made him a ſacrifice for our ſins: neither hath Chriſt reſiſted this counſell
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150476:11"/> and decrée of his heauenly Father, but hath fulfilled his will with a moſt ready minde,<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.9.</note> and loued vs, and hath deliuered himſelfe for our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.10.4. Can. 2.20.</note> hee hath loued vs, and hath deliuered himſelfe for vs: hee ſaith, <hi>I will be baptized with a certaine bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and how am I ſtraightened till it be fulfilled?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 12.50</note> This was the baptiſme of the Croſſe and tribulation, into which our moſt benigne Sauiour was altogether plunged, not for any other cauſe, but out of his great &amp; ineffable loue towards vs: this is that which hath ſo ſtraightened him, and driuen him; how great ſoeuer his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward griefe was in his paſſion, yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes his inner loue towards vs was greater and more ardent, through which hee was ready to ſuſtaine more things for our ſinnes, if the price for our redemption which hée payed had not ſéemed ſufficient. But there is no cauſe that we doubt of the ſufficiency of the price; with him there is altogether plentifull redemption, becauſe not a droppe but a ſtreame of bloud hath flowed largely through fiue parts of his body,<note place="margin">Born. ſer. <hi>22.</hi> ſup. cant. col. <hi>554.</hi>
                     </note> hee hath cryed out, that all things were finiſhed in the Croſſe and through the Croſſe, and therefore he hath made by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a full &amp; perfect purgation of our ſins, with one offring hath he for euer perfected thoſe which are ſanctified;<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3. Cap. 10.14. Apoc. 1.5.</note> he hath waſhed vs from our ſinnes in his bloud. Beléeue therefore, ſo cleere, ſo perſpicuous, ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words of the holy Ghoſt, and reſolue firmely, that by the death and paſſion of CHRIST, there is wrought a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150476:11"/> ſatiſfaction for thy ſinnes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>IIII.</hi> The memory of Actuall ſinnes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>PErchance Chriſt hath taken vpon himſelfe originall ſinne onely, ſo that for actuall ſinnes I my ſelfe muſt eyther ſatisfie or burne. Although therefore I reſolue firmely that through Chriſt I am waſhed from that origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſpot, yet thoſe actuall ſinnes doe vexe and preſſe me, which I haue committed through the whole courſe of my life, in number many, in weight moſt heauy, for deſert damnable. Chriſt is oppoſed to <hi>Adam,</hi> therefore the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Chriſt will not ſpread it ſelfe more wide then the fault that was deriued from <hi>Adam</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Another mans fault may be healed by another mans ſatisfaction, but a mans owne fault will require a mans owne ſatisfaction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>NAy, the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, the Sonne of God,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.7.</note> doth cleanſe thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together from all thy ſinnes, not that only which is deriued from <hi>Adam,</hi> but thoſe alſo which are heaped vpon this of thée. God hath ſet forth Chriſt the propitiatory by faith in his bloud,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.25.</note> to that may we draw néere by true faith, and hauing obtained remiſſion of our ſins be reconciled to God, as often as the weight and heape of our ſinnes doth preſſe vs downe: wee may come to this throne of grace with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that wee may obtaine mercy,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150476:12"/> finde grace in the ſeaſonable time of helpe. Furthermore, what redemption would this be? what reconciliation, if Chriſt had ſatiſfied for one onely kinde of ſinne, wée our ſelues being yet bound, and obliged to make ſatiſfaction for all the reſt farre more grieuous, and more copious? the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt is not ſo maimed, imperfect, and to halues,<note place="margin">Heb 10.12 14.18.</note> but offering one ſacrifice for ſinnes, by that one oblation hée hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected for euer thoſe that are ſanctified, and hath obtained ſuch a remiſſion of ſinnes, that there is not any other oblation neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for ſinnes.<note place="margin">1 Iohn. 2.1.2.</note> Wée haue an Aduocate with the Father, Ieſus Chriſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, he is the propitiation for our ſinnes, not for our ſinnes onely, but alſo for the ſinnes of the whole world. Therefore if hauing ſlipt into ſinnes out of the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the fleſh, wée doe earneſtly repent vs, wée haue a refuge ſet downe for vs in Chriſts interceſſion, the foundation of which interceſſion conſiſts in Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and ſatiſfaction, for from thence and therefore is Chriſts interceſſion effectuall for vs, becauſe a full and perfect ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was performed by him for our ſinnes; from thence and therefore the force of the Diuine iuſtice and ſeuere iudgement, due to our ſinnes, is not ſhaken againſt vs, becauſe Chriſt couers our ſinnes with the cloake of his mercie, the price of the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and deſerued redemption being paid of him. Let this therefore abide firme and ſure, that Chriſt by his death, the onely moſt true ſacrifice offered for vs, hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150476:12"/> purged, aboliſhed,<note place="margin">Auguſt. 4. <hi>de Trinit. ca.</hi> 13.</note> extinguiſhed whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer there was of ſinnes, from whence the principalities and powers did by right with-hold vs to ſuffer puniſhment; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in him and through him wée obtaine remiſſion not onely of originall ſinne,<note place="margin">1. <hi>De pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. etre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſ. ca</hi> 13. Tit. 2.14.</note> but alſo of the reſt of the ſinnes that we haue added there-vnto. For he (which thing day vp in thy déepeſt thoughts) hath giuen himſelfe for vs, that hée might redéeme vs from all iniquitie. Infinite is the perſon that hath ſatiſfied, how then ſhall not his Paſſion be of infinite merit? What is ſo deadly, that may not be healed by the death of the Sonne of God, which is life it ſelfe? what is ſo bloudie and ſo foule, but that it might be cleanſed by the pretious bloud of the Sonne of God?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> The doubting of the application of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Chriſt.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>BVt how may I be made partaker of that moſt pretious treaſure? Chriſt hath died for all, but now that fruit of the death of Chriſt doth not redound to all, whence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall I be aſſured, that the benefits of Chriſt doe alſo pertaine to me? whence may it appeare that I am in very deede and moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely a partaker of all thoſe things actually, which Chriſt hath deſerued for vs by his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and death?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150476:13"/>
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>GOD offers vnto thée the word of the Goſpell, and in the ſame all the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites of his Sonne.<note place="margin">Eſ. 6.5.2.</note> Hée ſpreads forth his hands all day, he calles, he inuites, verily therefore alſo he calles, he inuites, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticeth thée. That therefore which GOD offers vnto thée with the hand of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that embrace thou with the hand of firme confidence.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bern.</hi> Ser. <hi>31.</hi> ſup. can. Col. <hi>597.</hi>
                     </note> As farre as thou ſhalt ſtretch forth the foote of confidence in the goods of the Lord, ſo farre forth ſhalt thou poſſeſſe. God doth not put the oyle of his mercie, vnleſſe it be in the veſſell of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.<note place="margin">Id. Serm. <hi>3.</hi> in Annunc. Col. <hi>113.</hi>
                     </note> Thou ſhalt poſſeſſe ſo much of the goods of the Lord, as thou doeſt gather in the veſſell of confidence. For faith doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend Chriſt, in Chriſt God fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the remiſſion of ſinnes and life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. Heare concerning this thing, the words of the eternall and vnchangeable truth. So God loued the world, that he gaue his onely begotten Sonne,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.18.</note> that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one that beleeueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue eternall life. He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeueth in him is not iudged, but hath life eternall,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> for hée hath giuen power to all that haue receiued him to be made the Sonnes of God, to thoſe which beléeue on his name. This adoption comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all things, which are neceſſarie for vs to euerlaſting ſaluation: for if we be the Sonnes of God, then are we alſo borne of God.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertul.</hi> in apolo. c. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </note> For not the carnall generation, but the ſpirituall regeneration makes the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150476:13"/> Sonnes of God. If we are the Sonnes of God, then haue we alſo God fauourable vnto vs. For doth not a Father take pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his Sonnes?<note place="margin">Pſa. 103.13</note> If we are the Sonnes of God, then hath he alſo giuen vs his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, They which are lead by the ſpirit of God, theſe are the Sons of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.14 15.</note> for ye haue not receiued the ſpirit of bondage againe to feare, but ye haue receiued the ſpirit of adoption, in which we cry, <hi>Abba,</hi> Father. And againe,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> Becauſe you are Sonnes, God hath ſent the ſpirit of his Sonne into your hearts, crying <hi>Abba,</hi> Father.</p>
                  <p>To conclude,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.13</note> if we are the Sonnes of GOD, then are we alſo heires, heires of GOD, and heires annexed with Ieſus Chriſt; for who is he that is truly a Son without an inheritance? All theſe ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, ſo copious, and ſo various benefits are beſtowed vpon vs in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> and through Chriſt, which dwels in our harts, and is borne in vs ſpiritually through faith, which therefore the Scripture doth ſo often preach and commend vnto vs. <hi>Verily, verily,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.24.</note> 
                     <hi>I ſay vnto you</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>he, which heareth my word, and beleeues on him that hath ſent mee, hath eternall life, and comes not unto iudgement, but hath paſt from death to life. Hee that beleeueth in mee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.25 26.</note> 
                     <hi>although he were dead, yet ſhall he liue, and euery one which liueth and beleeueth in me, ſhall not dye for euer.<note place="margin">Ioh 7.36.39.</note> 
                        <hi>Hee that beleeueth in me, out of his belly ſhall flow Riuers of liuing water, which our Sauiour ſpeakes of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which they receiue that beleeue on him.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150476:14"/> Euery one that beleeueth in mee,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.46.</note> 
                        <hi>doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in darkneſſe, ſuppoſe it in the darkneſſe of ignorance, in the darkneſſe of ſinne, in the darkneſſe of eternall death, but by the light of faith hee is lead to the life of ſauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to the light of true righteouſneſſe, to the light of euerlaſting life.</hi> Nay, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle witneſſeth plainely, that all thoſe things which are written in the Goſpel, of the ſayings, doings, and ſufferings of Chriſt, are therefore written that by faith on his name wee may haue life. <hi>Becauſe God hath giuen vnto vs eternall life,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.11 12.13.</note> and this life is in his Sonne. Hee that hath the Sonne hath life; from thence we know that we haue euerlaſting life, becauſe wee beleeue on the name of the Sonne of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And not onely the Apoſtles and Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, but alſo all the Prophets, giue te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie to Chriſt. <hi>That all that beleeue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 10.43</note> 
                     <hi>receiue remiſſion of ſinnes through by name.</hi> That therefore which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> ſometimes ſaid to the keeper of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at Philippi, the ſame ſay I to thée: <hi>Beleeue on the Lord Ieſus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 16.31</note> 
                     <hi>and thou ſhalt be ſaued.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> The falſe perſwaſion of Faith.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>BVt I haue heretofore perceiued that very many doe put on a vaine perſwaſion of Faith, and deceiue themſelues with a falſe boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, what if I ſhould alſo be in the number of them? from whence may I be aſſured, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150476:14"/> my ſaith is a true and ſauing faith, and not a vaine and dead Image of faith?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>TRy and examine thy ſelfe, whether thou be in the faith, try thine owne ſelfe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5.</note> doeſt thou not know thine owne ſelfe, that Ieſus Chriſt is in thée? There want not firme and infallible inſtructions, by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rue and ſauing faith may be tried, knowne and diſcerned from idle and vaine boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng of faith. Firſt, then this is the nature of true faith, that it purifies the heart,<note place="margin">Act. 15.9.</note> and deſires to purge it cleane from the dregs of ſinns. For ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing that faith doth care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſéeke and deſire remiſſion of ſinnes, ſurely he that truly beléeues ſhall féele a ſerious ſorrow for the ſinnes that he hath committed. The Goſpell is preached to the poore, that is to ſay,<note place="margin">Matth. 11.6. Matth. 5.6.</note> to thoſe that are poore in ſpirit, which hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, which bring and offer to God a contrite heart, and an humbled ſpirit. Behold therefore the looking glaſſe of the Law, and the deformitie of thy crimes will appeare. Behold the ſhining face of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and it will appeare, that for the workes of darkneſſe which thou haſt followed, thou canſt not beare that light. Behold thy ſelfe, how grieuouſly the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe hath afflicted thée, which is the iuſt puniſhment of thy ſinnes, the ſcourge of the reuenging God, and the wages due to thy life which hath béene ſpent in ſinnes. He which ſinnes againſt his Creator,<note place="margin">Eccl 38.5.</note> fals into the hands of the Phyſitian. We haue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150476:15"/> loſt our health, becauſe wée haue offended our Creatour. They which follow the fleſh, are ſcourged in the fleſh. They ſigh in that, in which they haue ſinned. The cenſure of the puniſhment is in that, in which was the cauſe of ſhine. By how many thoughts, by how many words, by how many déedes haſt thou offended God? How faint hoſt thou béene aboue all things in the feare and loue of God? How ſlacke in Prayers, and other exerciſes of pietie? How barren in good workes? How oft haſt thou followed the perſwaſion of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, the ſeducing of the fleſh, the deceiuing of the world? Thoſe members which thou haſt oftentimes giuen as weapons to ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie and vnrighteouſneſſe, by the iuſt iudgement of GOD are now tormented with griefe and infirmitie. Acknowledge this and grieue, for if there be true and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious acknowledgement of ſinne in thy heart, immediately griefe of conſciences and deteſtation of ſinne will follow it. God is earneſtly angry with ſinnes, therefore out of the féeling of the wrath of God ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly bewaile thy ſinnes. GOD doth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely puniſh ſinnes, therefore puniſh in thy ſelfe by iuſt griefe, that which thou doeſt obſerue that thou haſt committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.<note place="margin">Pſa. 119.137.</note> Acknowledge the iudgement of God to be iuſt, and be thou humbled vnder his mighty hand. Neither haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect onely to thy outward faults, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the contagion of originall ſin, the fountaine of all euils;<note place="margin">Pſa. 90.9.</note> that indéede is hidden, but God placeth it in the light of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150476:15"/> his countenance, through it all the powers of ſoule and body are ſo weakened, that out of thy ſelfe, and by thy ſelfe thou canſt beginne no good, much leſſe performe it: through it thou art made ſubiect vnto death, and to all that troupe of calamities, miſeries, and diſeaſes, which goes before death.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Griefe inſufficient.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Acknowledge and feele, that I am not only borne and conceiued in ſinnes, but that I haue offended God by diuers, manifolde and great ſinnes. I feele this, and I earneſtly grieue, but that griefe perhaps is not ſufficient, ſeeing it doth not anſwere the fault, neither is it an aequiualent price for my ſinnes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>NAy, griefe riſing out of the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of ſinne, &amp; vexation of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall neuer be able to anſwere the grieuouſneſſe and deformitie of ſinnes, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God the infinite good, is that which is offended; ſinne the infinite euill, is that which is committed: the infinite puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Hell is prepared for ſinners, how then by thy contrition mighteſt thou ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the infinite iuſtice of God, and expiate his infinite wrath? Chriſt hath perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that, which of thy ſelfe, and by thy ſtrength, thou couldeſt not performe: hee hath payd the infinite and equiualent price for thy ſinnes. If by thine owne ſelfe thou
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150476:16"/> couldeſt haue ſatiſfied, if by thy contrition and by thy griefe thou haddeſt béene able to aboliſh ſinne, what néeded CHRIST to deſcend from heauen, and to labour ſo long vnder the burthen of his croſſe?<note place="margin">Eſa 43.24: Eſa. 63.3.</note> Thou haſt put him to paine in thy ſinnes, and preſſure in thine iniquities; he hath trodden the Wine-preſſe alone, and of the people there was none with him. Take héed therefore to thinke onely, that the griefe of thy contrition eyther can or ought to be ſuch that it may anſwere to the grieuouſneſſe and deformitie of thy ſinnes; but therefore, and to this end, God requires true acknowledgement of ſinne, and earneſt contrition of the heart, that place may be giuen to the frée remiſſion of ſinnes, which is giuen vnto thée through Chriſt, apprehended by faith. Chriſt preacheth the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Eſa 61.1.</note> but to the poore, <hi>that is,</hi> to thoſe that are humbled in ſpirit, he healeth,<note place="margin">Luke 4.2.18.</note> but the contrite in heart: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue they that are well néed of the Phiſition;<note place="margin">Mat. 9.12.</note> 
                     <hi>that is,</hi> which thinke that they are well: He preacheth libertie, but it is to the captiues; <hi>that is,</hi> to thoſe that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the ſpirituall captiuitie of ſin, for he deſires not to goe forth of bondage, which ſuppoſeth himſelfe by all meanes to be frée: He preacheth ſight, but it is to the blinde; <hi>that is,</hi> to thoſe that bewaile the ſpirituall blindneſſe of the heart, for they which ſay they ſée, their ſinne abideth: They which ſay that they are rich and wealthy,<note place="margin">ohn 9.41.</note> and want nothing, they doe not know that they are wretched, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150476:16"/> and poore, and blinde, and naked: Hee preacheth forgiueneſſe, but it is to the broken, and contrite in heart.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.6.</note> God kils and makes aliue, he leadeth downe to hell, and bringeth backe againe: he kils by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, that he may make aliue by conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he leadeth downe to hell by the ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the Law, that he may bring backe from hell by the comfort of the Goſpell.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> The weight of Griefe and Sorrow.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>TRoubles haue compaſſed mee round about, my heart is vexed and troubled, my ſinnes are alwayes before mine eyes, which do grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly torment my conſcience, and labour to beat mee downe to hell;<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.3.</note> there is no peace in my bones for the terrour of the Lord; my ſoule refuſeth to be comforted: I am troubled,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77. verſ. 2. ver. 3.</note> and my ſpirit doth afflict mee: I ſee no place whereto I may flye, and ſeeke a remedy of my ſinnes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>IF thou wilt flye, flye to CHRIST, he friendly inuites all that labour vnder the weight of their ſinnes,<note place="margin">Mat. 1.27</note> which are preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the yoake of iniquitie, an euill Miſtreſſe. Be thou hid in his wounds, and the tempeſt of the wrath of God will paſſe away. Chriſt is the propitiatory,<note place="margin">Rom 3 25</note> to which thou mayeſt flye with true faith, and reſt vnder the ſhadow of his wings. As the Hart deſireth the fountaines of waters,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.</note> ſo let thy ſoule, exhauſted with the heate of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150476:17"/> thy ſinnes, and of the wrath of God, thirſt after Chriſt the fountaine of liuing wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpringing forth to euerlaſting life. If thou commeſt vnto him, hee will not put thée backe, he will not repell thée; for thus goe his promiſes:<note place="margin">Apoc 22.17. Cap. 21.6.</note> 
                     <hi>He that thirſteth let him come, and hee that will, let him take the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life freely. I will giue vnto him that thirſteth of the Well of the water of life freely. Come vnto me all yee which labour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 11.27</note> 
                     <hi>and are heauy loaden, and I will refreſh you; in mee, and by mee you ſhall finde reſt to your ſoules. Him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 6.37.</note> 
                     <hi>that comes vnto me, I will not caſt forth of dores.</hi> Imbrace theſe words of Chriſt, which are the words of the eternall and vnchangeable truth, with a faithfull heart. Let thy heart ſet before him theſe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.8.</note> and ſéeke the face of the Lord. Set Chriſt as it were, in the middeſt betwéene thée a ſinner, and thy angry God: appeale from the Throne of Gods ſeuere iuſtice, to the Throne of mercy, prepared for thée in Chriſt, and through Chriſt. The internall Hawke doth vrge and purſue thy ſoule,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.14</note> let it flye therefore like a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and affrighted Doue to the holes of the Rocke, which are the wounds of Chriſt. <hi>Moſes</hi> doth accuſe thée, ſigh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Bern. Serm. <hi>64.</hi> ſup. Cant. Auguſt in meditat.</note> that Chriſt may make interceſſion for thée. Thy conſcience is troubled, but let it not be tumbled downe from his hope and confidence, but let it remember the wounds of Chriſt: let all the aſſurance of thy confidence bee in the wounds of Chriſt, which do abound with the ſtreams of mercy; neither want there holes through
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150476:17"/> which they may flow out.<note place="margin">Idem Serm. <hi>22.</hi> ſup. Cant.</note> Let the paſſion of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt be thy laſt refuge, and onely remedy of thy ſinnes: wiſedome failing, righteouſneſſe not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing, the merits of holineſſe not holding out, that will be able to helpe and ſuccour thée.</p>
                  <p>And this is the other, and indéede eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall propertie of true Faith; forſooth, to behold with the eye of the heart, Chriſt hanging on the Croſſe, out of his wounds to hope for, and drawe the medicine of her wounds, to rely on him with a true confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of heart, and to wrap her ſelfe as it were, in his moſt holy merit; for this is the voyce of true faith:
<q>
                        <l>Behold me, thou which hangst vpon the Tree,<note place="margin">Bern. Serm. <hi>22.</hi> ſup. Cant.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>And let my ſinnes in thy ſide hidden be:</l>
                        <l>My ſicke ſoule thirſts for thee, my guilt forgiue,</l>
                        <l>My ſinne's my death, but in thy bloud I liue.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore, if hauing compunction for thy ſinnes, thou hungerſt and thirſteſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter righteouſneſſe, thou mayeſt beléeue on him which iuſtifieth the wicked, and being iuſtified by faith alone, thou ſhalt haue peace with God. Confeſſe that thou art not worthy, neither canſt thou by thine owne merits obtaine the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; but let this be thy confidence, that Chriſt thy Lord doth obtaine it by a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble name, <hi>that is,</hi> by the inheritance of the Father, and by the merit of his Paſſion: with the one, he himſelfe is content, the other hee giues to thée: from whoſe gift challenging it to thy ſelfe, thou ſhalt not be confounded.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150476:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> The temptation of Deſperation.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>THE Deuill doth ſollicite mee to deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> would haue thée deſpaire but in thy ſelf, and of thy ſelfe, becauſe thou art a ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.21</note> but not in God, whoſe grace doth abound aboue ſinne: for as much as a drop is to the Sea,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>3.</hi> de Poen.</note> ſo much is mans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice to Gods mercy. The Sea though it be great, yet it hath a meaſure; but the cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of God hath no meaſure: neither deſpaire thou of Chriſt, and in Chriſt, which came into the world, that he might ſaue ſinners;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15.</note> whoſe blood doth more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile to the reconciliation of God, then the ſinnes of the whole world to his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Although thy ſinnes be great, and diuers, and oft-times doubled, yet they are not greater or more grieuous then that thou mayeſt obtaine pardon &amp; forgiuenes of them, ſéeing the goodnes of God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the iniquitie of all men. Sins are in their fall, but the grace of God is in its riſing. Sins are in the works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and Man; to take pitty, to ſpare, &amp; to remit are the workes of God: by how much therefore God is more mighty then the Diuell and Man, by ſo much alſo his mercy is greater then our malice. <hi>The Lord is full of compaſſion and mercy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.8 verſ. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſſe. Hee will not alwayes chide, neither will hee keepe his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150476:18"/> for euer.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">verſ. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee hath not dealt with vs after our ſinnes, nor rewarded vs after our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">verſ. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>For as high as the Heauen is aboue the Earth, ſo great is his mercy toward them that feare him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">verſ. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>As farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo farre hath hee remoued our ſinnes from vs.</hi> The Heauen is incomparably greater then the Earth, which is no big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then the leaſt point in reſpect of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: ſo the mercy of the heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is incomparably greater then all ſinnes: farre be it, farre be it therefore from thée, that thou ſay, Greater is mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie then the pietie of the pittying God. Thou ſhalt finde God more kinde then thou art culpable.<note place="margin">Bern. ſerm. <hi>11.</hi> ſup. Can. Col. <hi>5 18.</hi> Gerſon. de remed. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Puſilla.</note> So great is the mercy of God, that if thou hadſt all the ſinnes of the world vpon thée, and didſt grieue, that with thy ſinnes thou hadſt proudly offended thy God, ſo good a Lord, and ſhouldeſt firmely purpoſe hereafter to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, God would neuer condemne thée. What?<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>55.</hi>
                     </note> doſt thou ſo forget the ſatiſfaction performed of Chriſt, that thou wilt prefer thy ſinnes before Chriſts merit, <hi>that is,</hi> thy ſelfe before God? Doſt thou ſée the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the diſeaſe, and doſt thou not ſée the power of the Phyſitian? Great are thy ſinnes, farre greater is Chriſt, which hath ſatiſfied for thy ſinnes. Diuers are thy ſinnes, but Chriſt alſo hath ſuffered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers things for thée. GOD is the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite good whom thou haſt offended by thy ſinnes, but Chriſt is an infinite perſon, which hath reconciled thée to God: ſigh therefore to thy heauenly Father, and pray
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150476:19"/> in the name of his Sonne thy Sauiour: if thou doeſt deſpiſe mee,<note place="margin">Anſel. de redemp. gen. hum. fol. <hi>96.</hi>
                     </note> O eternall God for mine iniquitie, as I haue deſerued, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard me at leaſt, taking pitty on mee, for the loue of thy beloued off-ſpring. Regard that in thy Sonne which thou mayſt bee mercifull vnto in thy ſeruant. Sée the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his fleſh, and forgiue the guilt of my fleſh, remember what thy good Son hath ſuffered, and forget what thine euill ſeruant hath wrought.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> The tentation of Blaſphemie.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Am conſtrained to confeſſe that I am not onely prouoked to deſperation, but that I am alſo ſometimes tempted with the ſpirit of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie; for ſuch thoughts doe ariſe in my heart, as are iniurious againſt God himſelfe my Creatour, and my Sauiour. I would chuſe to dye a thouſand times, that I might be freed from this tentation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>THeſe cogitations are not the actions of thy heart, but rather the moſt bitter paſſions, ſéeing thou art not delighted with theſe cogitations, but doeſt féele out of them ſorrowes more bitter then death it ſelfe. They are the ſcourges of Satan, with which hee doth afflict and torment thée, they ſhall not be imputed to thée of the Lord for ſinne. And be it, that ſome impatience of the heart do ariſe out of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150476:19"/> infirmitie of the fleſh, yet God knowes thy groanings and thy ſighes: yea, the weight of tentations hath wringed out of <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Ieremy</hi> hard words, which the moſt benigne God hath fatherly forgiuen them. Obſerue out of them, how thou haſt alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether no ſtrength to good out of thy ſelfe, that with the whole truſt of thy hart thou mayeſt learne to cleaue vnto God. This is the force and higheſt degrée of the fight againſt Satan, take héed thou faint not here, the mighty God that appoints thée to this combat, will be preſent with thée, neither will hee leaue thée deſtitute of his helpe. Expect patiently and humbly, till thou mayeſt be fréed from the fiery darts of Satan; in the meane time,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.16</note> let the grace of the Lord ſuffice thée.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> It is the fleſh which doth thus wraſtle with the ſpirit, and ſhewes it ſelfe ready and pliable to take the darts of Satan: the ſinne that dwels in thy fleſh ſhall not be imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, if thou wilt mortifie by the ſpirit the déedes of the fleſh, and wilt not giue conſent to theſe blaſphemous cogitations. Extinguiſh thoſe fiery darts of Satan in the bloud of Chriſt, turne againſt them the Buckler of faith, and aſſoone as thou ſhalt perceiue any ſuch blaſphemous cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to ariſe, betake thy ſelfe to prayers, by which thou mayeſt trample it downe, as it were in the firſt growth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150476:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> The particularitie of the Promiſes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Feele ſome conſolation of the ſpirit in my heart: I obſerue a certaine truſt in my ſoule, which forbids mee to deſpaire, when I behold the mercy of God abounding aboue ſinnes, and the merit of Chriſt, which is of infinite price and value. But I doubt whether that promiſe in the Goſpell of the mercy of God and merit of Chriſt doth pertaine to me alſo: for God is not only mercifull, but alſo a moſt iuſt and ſeuere reuenger of ſinnes; and that all are not made partakers of the benefits of Chriſt, experience, to my great griefe, doth witneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>TAke héed that thou giue no place to thoſe ſeducing thoughts of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of the promiſes of the Goſpell. God calleth all vnto him, hee deſires all to come vnto him, hee offers the word of the Goſpell to all, and in it the benefits of Chriſt: neither doth hee this fainedly, but in earneſt: not hypocritical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but with a minde to communicate them: <hi>I liue</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I will not the death of a ſinner that dyes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eze. 18.31 32. cap. 33. ver. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>but that he may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and liue.</hi> Thou heareſt the ſerious oath of the diuine truth: Thou heareſt that their conuerſion is expected and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of God, which dye in their ſinnes by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150476:20"/> their owne fault: thou heareſt that ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intreatie twiſe repeated: <hi>Come vnto mee, all yee</hi> (ſayth our Sauiour, the meane and meſſenger of the heauenly Father:) <hi>Come vnto mee, all yee, all ye which labour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 11.28</note> 
                     <hi>and are heauy laden, and I will refreſh you.</hi> Thou heareſt that the way lyes open to Chriſt for al that labour vnder the yoake of their ſinne, and that refreſhing and reſt of ſoule is promiſed to them. God will haue all men to be ſaued, ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4</note> being taught it in the third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and to come to the knowledge of the truth. Hee hath ſhut vp all vnder vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, that hee might haue mercy vpon all.<note place="margin">Rom. 11.20.23.</note> Thou heareſt, that the ſaluation of all is deſired, and ſought of God, that the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God is open vnto all: no body is excluded here, but hee which doth exclude himſelfe:</p>
                  <p>There is one GOD of all, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee deſireth that all ſhould be ſaued whom he hath made.<note place="margin">Primaſ. in H. L.</note> One hath giuen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the price of redemption for all, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hée would haue all to bee partakers of that price. GOD would not haue any to periſh, ſayth <hi>Peter,</hi> being taught by his owne example,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.9.</note> but that all returne to repentance.</p>
                  <p>Thou heareſt, that the long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and goodneſſe of GOD doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite all to repentance, and that GOD would not the deſtruction of any. Take héede that thou ſpeake not againſt this ſo cleare and ſo manifeſt a truth, againſt theſe ſayings of the holy Ghoſt, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150476:21"/> as it were, with a beame of the Sunne, let the conſolations of the Scripture be of more force with thée, then the thoughts of thine owne heart: for the Scripture is the word of the liuing God, which neuer deceiues, but our heart is lying, and deceiueth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> The abſolute decree of Reprobation.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>THe promiſe indeede outwardly is offered vnto all, but God hath made from euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting a decree of the Reprobation of ſome men, whom hauing caſt from him, he hath adiudged them to eternall torments, to theſe though he offer the word outwardly, yet they cannot communicate or partake of the good things in the word. Perhaps I alſo am in the number of thoſe reprobates?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>THE ſecrets of heauen, let no creature on earth preſume to pry into: Enough is reuealed both for our conſolation and ſaluation. Whom God hath predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we know not; it is a ſecret of Gods Priuie Counſell, where-into wée are not admitted. And how farre forth, and in what manner God may pleaſe to worke and bring about a purpoſe of his owne, without the endeauour and purpoſe of man, we know not, that alſo is a ſecret of Gods Priuie Counſell, where-into wée are not admitted. And therefore as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the ſecret things belong to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150476:21"/> Lord our GOD;</hi> ſo to him and his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, be content to leaue them. But this we all know, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> bids vs <hi>make our election ſure</hi> by the practiſe of good workes, and holy duties of Religion; and telleth vs, that <hi>hee that doth thoſe things, ſhall neuer fall.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. that is, ſuch a one ſhall neuer faile of grace or glorie. And therefore while thou endeauoureſt to liue in all good conſcience according to Gods will; thou mayeſt haue peace of conſcience in Gods promiſes and mercies. And this wée know, that our Sauiour commandeth, and promiſeth; <hi>Aske and yee ſhall haue; ſeeke and ye ſhall finde; knocke and it ſhall be opened vnto you:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou vſe the meanes, thou canſt not doubt of the end.</p>
                  <p>Finally, this we all know alſo, that God proteſteth vpon his word, yea vpon his oath, that he <hi>deſireth not the death of him that dieth,</hi> or taketh <hi>any pleaſure that the wicked ſhould die,</hi> but that he <hi>may returne and liue. Ezek</hi> 18.23.32. <hi>&amp; Ezek.</hi> 33.11. And therefore God is ſo farre from reiecting thée before thou haſt ſinned; that hée is moſt readie to admit of thée after thou haſt ſinned. Onely then endeauour to doe the workes of him that ſent thée into the world; begge and craue for grace and mercie from the Father of mercies; ſearch thy heart, finde out thy ſinnes, and each day renue thy repentance: and then be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that the outward offering of grace will euer be accompanied with the inward working of the ſpirit. For the promiſes of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150476:22"/> Gods mercies are generall <hi>to all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue on him. Rom.</hi> 10.11. <hi>To all that call on the name of the Lord Rom</hi> 10.13. <hi>To all that labour and groane vnder the burden of their ſinnes. Matth.</hi> 11.28. <hi>To all that feare God, and worketh righteouſneſſe. Act.</hi> 10.35. <hi>&amp;c. And the merites, and death, and Paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, as they are offered, ſo they are beſtowed on all generally, that lay hold on him for their Sauiour. Ioh.</hi> 3.16.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> The doubting of the application of the merit of Chriſt.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>LEt the merit of Chriſt be, and be ſaid to ſpread it ſelfe wide, in the meane time I doe not yet ſee for mine owne particular that the benefits of Chriſt are offered and applied to me. Many things are offered to men in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, which notwithſtanding doe not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to euery man in particular.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>NAy, from the generall we may wel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede to the particular, from that which is common, to that which is more reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Therefore becauſe God would haue all to be ſaued, thou mayeſt rightly and moſt firmely ſubſume, that he would haue thée alſo to be ſaued. Becauſe Chriſt is ſaid to haue died for all, thou maieſt rightly and moſt firmely ſubſume, that he alſo died on the Croſſe for thée, and will cleanſe thée from all thy ſinnes by his bloud: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he calleth all repenting; he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thée repenting. And becauſe he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150476:22"/> grace and life to all that beleeue, depend, and relie on him; therefore he will performe it to thée, when thou doeſt reſt and relie on him for his mercies. Yea, and that which God promiſeth to all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall by his word, that he applieth to thée is particular in the Miniſterie of the word. Onely ſubmit thy ſelfe to the wholeſome Miniſterie of reconciliation,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.18.</note> which God hath committed to the Miniſters of the Church,<note place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> to the keyes that he hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt, to the office of Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vndergoe in the name of Chriſt, God exhorting, and as it were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating vs by them. And then that which is ſpecially offered vnto thée, do not doubt but that ſpecially it belongs vnto thée. When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the ſerious ſorrowe of thy b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> heareth the voice of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, pronouncing remiſſion of ſins in the name of Chriſt, reſolue that thou heareſt Chriſt himſelfe: what ſo is héere done in the name of Chriſt, that doth Chriſt doe. It is Chriſt which pronounceth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes vnto thée, the Miniſter doth onely lend his voice to Chriſt. If any doubting would inſinuate it ſelfe into thy hart therof, attend to the words of Chriſt, ſpeaking to the Apoſtles &amp; their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 10.16 Matth. 10.20. Ioh. 1.23.</note> 
                     <hi>It is not you that ſpeak, but the ſpirit of my Father.</hi> Attend to the words of the Baptiſt: <hi>I am the voice of a cryer.</hi> There is another which doth preach and cry by me, the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is mine, but the force and benefit of the Miniſterie dependes of another.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150476:23"/> Attend to the words of the Apoſtle. For Chriſt (that is in the name and place of Chriſt) we are Embaſſadours,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.20.</note> God as it were exhorting by vs, we beſéech you for Chriſt, be you reconciled vnto GOD. <hi>He therfore which contemnes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.8</note> 
                     <hi>contemnes not man but God, which hath giuen his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into vs.</hi> Beleeue therefore, that euen at this day Chriſt ſaith to thée, that which heeretofore hee hath ſaide to the man ſicke of the Palſie,<note place="margin">Matth. 9.2. Luc. 7.48.</note> and to the woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinner, <hi>Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no difference betwéene that, and this which the Miniſter vtters, for this is not pronounced of man, and that of Chriſt. When therefore thou heareſt the Miniſter pronounce vnto thée the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes, doe not thinke that thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the voice of the Miniſter, but the voice of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIIII.</hi> The want of the euidence of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the word.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Confeſſe that there is great and notable conſolation offered vnto mee in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the word, as yet notwithſtanding my faith wauers, neither doth it ſo firmely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the promiſe of the Goſpell, that it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all temptation: for my fleſh whiſpers vnto mee; that the promiſes are onely words, which thou perceiueſt with thine eares, but thou doeſt not as yet ſee the good promiſes ſubiect to thine eyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150476:23"/>
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>INdéed, they are words: but the words of the moſt true and euerliuing God. They are words indéed,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.69.</note> but the words of Spirit and life. They are words indéed, but more firme and durable then this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen which thou beholdeſt, then this earth whereon thou ſtandeſt.<note place="margin">Luk. 21.33</note> 
                     <hi>Heauen and Earth ſhall paſſe away, but my words ſhall not paſſe away,</hi> ſaith the truth.<note place="margin">Eſa. 40.8.</note> 
                     <hi>The word of our Lord God abides for euer,</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Hée which foldeth himſelfe in this word, hée which embraceth it with true faith, the ſame may be ſaued for euer. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath God onely ſet forth vnto thée his word, but to his word he hath added Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,<note place="margin">Auguſtin. <hi>tract.</hi> 80. <hi>in</hi> Iohan.</note> which are as it were the viſible word, viſible ſignes of the inuiſible grace, and ſeales of the promiſes of God, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for the confirmation and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy faith. By Baptiſme thou art receiued into the couenant of the grace of God, thou art made a Sonne and heire of GOD, thou art waſhed by the bloud of Chriſt from thy ſinnes, thou are regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and renued by the holy Ghoſt, and as I may ſpeake in a word, art made truly partaker of al heauenly goods. For Chriſt attributes to Baptiſme, that it is a meane of regeneration.<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Vnleſſe a man be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of water and of the ſpirit, hee ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of heauen. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he which is borne againe of the water of Baptiſme and the ſpirit, is written an heire of eternall life, becauſe it is a meanes of ſaluation.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150476:24"/> Hee that ſhall beleeue and be baptized, ſhall be ſaued.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 16.16</note> The Apoſtles doe attribute to baptiſme,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.6.</note> that it is the lauacre of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and renouation in the holy Ghoſt, when we are baptized into the remiſſion of ſinnes.<note place="margin">Mar. 1.4.</note> Let euery one of you be baptized, ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 2.38.</note> in the name of Ieſus, into the remiſſion of ſinnes, and you ſhall receiue the gift of the holy Ghoſt. Baptiſme doth ſaue vs,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.12</note> (ſaith he in another place) which is not the putting off of the filth of the fleſh, but the requeſt of a good conſcience, or a couenant to Godwards, through the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt. Be thou baptized,<note place="margin">Act. 22.16</note> and waſh away thy ſinnes (ſaith <hi>Ananias.</hi>) As many of you as are baptized haue put on Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.27.</note> and by faith ye are the ſonnes of God, ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> For Chriſt ſanctifieth his Church,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.27</note> clenſing it in the Lauer of water in his word. Out of all which thou mayeſt firmely conclude, that baptiſme is the price of redemption to the captiues,<note place="margin">Baſill. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. tom. <hi>1.</hi> part. <hi>446. Cyril.</hi> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolym. in praefat. Catech.</note> the forgiuing of debts, the death of ſinne: regeneration, the bright cloathing of the ſoule, a ſeale that cannot be infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the chariot to Heauen, the procurer of the kingdome, the frée gift of adoption. Illumination or Baptiſme is the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſoules, the change of life, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the conſcience vnto God, the help of our weakneſſe: Illumination is the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off of the fleſh, the following of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nazian.</hi> orat. in S. Bap. p. <hi>615.</hi>
                     </note> the communion of the word: Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination is the reſtitution of the Image, the deluge of ſin, the participation of light, the looſing of darkeneſſe: Illumination
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150476:24"/> is the Waggon or Chariot vnto God, the peregrination with Chriſt, the foundation of faith, the perfecting of the minde, the glory of the kingdome of Heauen, the change of life, the taking away of bondage, the looſing of bands, the inſtauration of the couenant.<note place="margin">Tertull. <hi>4.</hi> Aduer. Marc. p. <hi>231.</hi>
                     </note> It is the originall of true life and of true iuſtice, it is a compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous waſhing, it is the ſacrament of life, and ſaluation eternall.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>The holy Ghoſt into this Brooke doth come</l>
                     <l>From Heauen,<note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>21</hi> contra Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcen. c <hi>18.</hi> Paulinus Epiſt. <hi>12</hi> ad Seuer.</note> and brooding on the front ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall</l>
                     <l>Doth heat the holy waters: they become</l>
                     <l>Conceiued of GOD, and in their liqours chriſtall.</l>
                     <l>Bring forth an holy Brood, an holy Nation.</l>
                     <l>Of the eternall ſeed the propagation.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>For what the grace of God doth worke inuiſibly in our baptiſme, that hath béene ſhewed in viſible ſignes in the Baptiſme of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mnit. in cap. <hi>17.</hi> Harmoni.</note> The water of baptiſme was ſanctified by the touching of the Lords body, for what things ſoeuer Chriſt hath deſerued and purchaſed in the body of his fleſh, he hath as it were, layd them downe in baptiſme. He tooke vpon him baptiſme with vs ſinners, that hee might witneſſe that by baptiſme wee are made his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. As the eternall Father in the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of CHRIST vttered this voyce: <hi>This is my beloued Sonne,</hi> ſo as yet this day, all that doe beléeue and are baptized, hée doth adopt for Sonnes.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150476:25"/> As in the baptiſme of Chriſt Heauen was opened, ſo as yet at this day by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſme the gate of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Paradiſe is opened vnto vs. As in the baptiſme of Chriſt the holy Ghoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended vpon him in the ſhape of a Doue, ſo the holy Ghoſt is preſent in our bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and workes therein effectually our regeneration and renouation, ſo that by this reaſon, in Baptiſme doe concurre the grace of the Father adopting, the merit of the Sonne clenſing, and the efficacie of the holy Ghoſt regenerating. Therefore if thou art baptized, thou mayſt not doubt of the grace of God, the remiſſion of ſins, and the promiſe of eternall ſaluation, ſo thou continue in that faith which there thou didſt profeſſe. Baptiſme is the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of regeneration, where there is rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, there is the remiſſion of ſinnes, there is the grace of God, there is perfect iuſtice, there is renuing, there is the gift of the holy Ghoſt, there is adoption, there is the inheritance of eternall life.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XV</hi> The falling out of the Couenant of Baptiſme.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Beleeue indeed, that I am receiued into the couenant of Gods grace by the Sacrament of Baptiſme, that I haue attained remiſſion of my ſinnes, and am written in the Booke of life, but by my ſinnes I haue againe fallen out of the grace of this Couenant, by commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150476:25"/> offences againe: I haue made the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion paſt of none effect, and haue often deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that I ſhould be blotted out of the Booke of life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>NAy, the Couenant of GOD is an euerlaſting couenant,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.13.1. Col. 2.11.</note> to which after thy ſinnes thou mayeſt againe betake thy ſelfe by true and earneſt repentance. For euen as God ſpeakes of the Sacrament of circumciſion that it is an eternall coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: ſo let vs not doubt but that God will enter into and ſtabliſh with vs an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting couenant in baptiſme, which hath ſucceeded in the place of circumciſion: <hi>I will marry thee vnto mee for euer,</hi> ſayth he by the Prophet,<note place="margin">Hoſe 2.19</note> 
                     <hi>I will mary thee vnto mee in righteouſnes, and iudgement, in mercy, and in compaſſion. I will marry thee vnto me in faith. The hils ſhall be moued,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſa. 54.10.</note> 
                     <hi>and the valleyes ſhall tremble, but my mercy ſhall not depart from thee, and the couenant of my peace ſhall not be moued, ſaith thy Lord that taketh pitty.</hi> God forbid therefore, God forbid,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.3</note> that we ſay that the faith of God can be made of none effect by the incredulitie of men: If we doe neuer ſo much take away credit from his words, or depart from him,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.13.</note> hée remaineth faithfull, alwayes like himſelfe, true and conſtant, he cannot deny himſelfe, Therefore though thou ſometime ſinne out of thine inbred infirmitie, thou doeſt not forthwith fall out of the couenant of God. Indéed, by ſinnes committed againſt knowledge and conſcience, thou doſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150476:26"/> prouoke GOD againſt thée, and make him to be ſometimes angry, but by true repentance thou returneſt againe into his grace and fauour. The ſhip of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme doth not floate away from vs,<note place="margin">Secunda poſt naufra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulu.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee leape out of it into the Sea of ſinnes, therefore by repentance, which in this ſence may be called a ſecond planke after ſhipwracke, wee may returne againe to the ſame ſhippe of baptiſme, that in it wée may bee brought to the hauen of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Hier. in ca. <hi>3.</hi> Eſa. ver. <hi>9.</hi> Tertu. lib. de poenit. p. <hi>479.</hi>
                     </note>Therefore, imbrace repentance, as hée that is ſhipwracke the helpe of ſome boord, or plancke, this will lift thée vp, being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed with the waues of thy ſins, &amp; will bring thée into the hauen of the cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of God. <hi>Peter</hi> had denied his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.21</note> but being conuerted, he doth neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe ſeeke the promiſe of ſaluation in baptiſme. The Galathians had fallen grieuouſly, and likewiſe the Corinthians: notwithſtanding the Apoſtle doth ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them conſolation, deriued out of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, after that they were againe raiſed vp by repentance:<note place="margin">Gal. 3.17.</note> pronouncing as many of them as were baptized, to haue put on Chriſt: nay, manifeſtly affirming, that they were clenſed, and baptized in one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, into one body, that is to ſay, a miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body. Out of which it euidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that the efficacy of the couenant of Baptiſme doth extend it ſelf to the time to come, neither is it made plainely of no force, and aboliſht by the fall of man into ſinne, but that that couenant abides la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150476:26"/> firme,<note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>1.</hi> de nupt. &amp; concupiſ. cap. <hi>33.</hi>
                     </note> and ratified of the part of God. That therefore which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that Chriſt did clenſe the Church in the Lauer of water in the word, is ſo to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that by the ſame Lauer of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and word of ſanctification all the euils of regenerate men are altogether clenſed and healed, not onely the ſinnes paſt, all which are remitted in Baptiſme, but alſo thoſe which are afterwards contracted by humane ignorance or infirmitie, not that baptiſme ſo often as men ſinne may ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten be repeated, but becauſe by that which is once giuen, the pardon of what ſoeuer ſinnes is obtained for the faithfull, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before, but alſo afterwards, vpon their true and vnfained repentance. Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therefore, and bewaile thy ſinnes, yet neyther deny the couenant of grace that was begunne with thée in baptiſme, nor forget it: but though thou fall a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, yet returne and goe backe. <hi>Returne vnto mee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 3.12.</note> 
                     <hi>O thou ſoule that art tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned away, ſaith the LORD, and I will not turne away my face from you,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.8.</note> 
                     <hi>becauſe I am mercifull, ſayth the LORD, and I will not be angry for euer.</hi> Let thy heart ſet this word before GOD,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.13.</note> and hée will take pitty vpon thée, being mindfull of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for hée cannot deny himſelfe and his word.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:150476:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertaine taking into the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Baptiſme.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The tempted.</head>
                  <p>BVT whence may I bee aſcertained, that after I haue fallen, by true repentance I may be receiued againe of God into fauour? I would to God my heart might be confirmed by ſome certaine ſeale, I would there were ſome Sacrament by the participation whereof that promiſe of grace might be ſealed vp vnto mee?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>YEa, there is ſuch a Sacrament, that is to ſay, the moſt holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper, in which Chriſt giues vnto thée his moſt precious body and blood. Wherefore, when they receiueſt the moſt holy price of thy redemption, that is to ſay, the body and bloud of Chriſt in that holy ſupper, thou mayeſt be ſure, that thou art made truly partaker of all thoſe things, which Chriſt hath deſerued on the altar of the Croſſe, by the deliuering vp of his body, and powring out of his bloud, <hi>that is,</hi> the fauour of God, remiſſion of ſinnes, righteouſneſſe, life, and euerlaſting ſaluation. When thou drinkeſt that bloud, by the pouring out whereof the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of grace was ſtricken and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: how canſt thou doubt whether thou be againe receiued into that couenant, and into the fauour of God? What is more néere vnto God then his onely begotten
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150476:27"/> Sonne? as who is in his boſome,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.18.</note> which is in the Father, and the Father in him, which is one with the Father. Againe, what is more néere to the Sonne of God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.10</note> then fleſh and bloud, or the humane nature which hee hath aſſumed?<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.30</note> as which he hath coupled to himſelfe in a perſonall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble league. Therefore, by eating the fleſh of Chriſt, and drinking his bloud thou art ioyned moſt ſtraightly vnto God. Theſe things being taken, &amp; taken down,<note place="margin">Hilar. <hi>8.</hi> de Trin. p. <hi>141.</hi>
                     </note> make that Chriſt abides in thée, and thou in Chriſt. What is more néere vnto vs, then that which wee eate and drinke, as which is eyther conuerted into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of our fleſh, as natural and elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall meates, or elſe doth change and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert vs into it, as that ſpiritual food of the body and blood of the Lord, which we eate indéed, but we doe not change it into our ſubſtance, but wee are changed into it. Therefore, by eating the quickening fleſh of Chriſt, thou receiueſt ſpirituall life from the ſame, by drinking the precious bloud of Chriſt, thou comeſt to the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt hath taken vpon him the humane nature of vs, in it he hath condemned ſin, he hath deſtroyed death, hee hath repaired life, and hath filled the ſame with the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of grace, and heauenly good things: the ſame nature taken from vs, and repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in himſelfe, ſanctified and filled with heauenly treaſures hee ſets before thée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the holy Supper, that thou mayſt be aſcertained that thoſe things doe truly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150476:28"/> pertaine vnto thée, which hee hath layd downe into the ſame, as it were into a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine rich ſtorehouſe; he doth as it were, ingraft thy wretched and depraued nature into his moſt holy and quickening fleſh, that out of it thou mayeſt draw the iuyce of life, and an antidote of the ſpirituall poyſon that lyes hidden in thy fleſh. He is the Vine, we are the braunches, hee that abides in him,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hn 15.5</note> and he in whom he abides, this man brings forth much fruit. The vncleannneſſe of thy nature is ſhadowed and couered by that moſt holy body of Chriſt which thou receiueſt, and by that moſt precious bloud, which thou drinkeſt, leaſt it appeare before the tribunall and in the ſight of God.<note place="margin">Liturg. vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Damaſ. <hi>4.</hi> fid. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </note> Therefore thou recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt the fleſh and bloud of Chriſt for an apology that will eaſily be admitted, and the earneſt of eternall life: to the ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; kéeping of the body and the ſoule, to the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and to life euerlaſting. Nay, in the holy Supper is giuen thée a certaine holeſome prouiſion for thy iourney, ſéeing the tokens of the future reſurrection are exhibited vnto thée,<note place="margin">Can. Nicen.</note> by which the right of acquaintance and hoſpitalitie which is to be expected in the heauenly countrey, is confirmed vnto thée.<note place="margin">Iohn 6.54.</note> 
                     <hi>He which eateth my fleſh,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and drinkes my bloud, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him vp againe in the laſt day.</hi> It cannot therefore come to paſſe, I ſay, that thy body ſhould abide in the graue, ſéeing it is nouriſhed with the body and bloud of our Lord, that is to ſay, with that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150476:28"/> food which is the medicine of immortality, the antidote that wée ſhould not dye, but liue in God through Chriſt, the purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that driues away all euill. By this foode thy weakeneſſe ſhall be comforted, that thou mayeſt come through with <hi>Elias,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Reg. 13.21.</note> to the hill of the Lord. The bones of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus,</hi> yea, euen when he was dead, did giue life, by how much more the fleſh of Chriſt liuing and quickening, receiued by faith, ſhall quicken thee to euerlaſting life.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> The vnworthy vſe of the holy Supper.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Acknowledge that in the true and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vſe of the holy ſupper, the godly are made partakers of theſe benefits, but it doth not a little trouble mee, that the Apoſtle doth affirme, that they which eate this bread vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.27</note> and drinke this cup of the Lord vnworthily, are made guiltie of the body and bloud of the Lord. I feare therefore, leſt that I be an vnworthy gueſt of this heauenly ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>BY acknowledging and bewailing of thine vnworthines, thou mayeſt eſcape the ſpot and imputation of an vnworthy gueſt: for the Apoſtle calles vnworthy, not thoſe which are weake in faith, wheras this ſacrament was inſtituted for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of faith, &amp; comfort of the weake, but thoſe which doe not proue themſelues neither do diſcerne the Lords body, <hi>that is,</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:150476:29"/> which come to this holy Supper,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.29.</note> as it were to a common banquet, without true repentance and liuely faith, without the hatred of ſinne, and a ſerious and earneſt purpoſe of amendement of life, which doe not diſcerne this heauenly banquet from other common foode, that they may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the true excellency thereof, and vſe due preparation of the hart thereunto. Such vnworthy gueſts of this banquet, do nothing leſſe ſin in eating and drinking vnworthily the fleſh and bloud of Chriſt, then the Iewes in crucifying Chriſt. But farre be it from thy pietie, farre be it, I ſay, that thou ſhouldeſt be in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> Thou doeſt acknowledge alſo the ſpots of thy ſinnes, thou doeſt bewaile the vncleaneneſſe of thy nature, thou ſigheſt vnto Chriſt the Phyſitian of thy ſoule, that he prepare a ſit lodging for himſelfe in thy heart, thou weigheſt the greatneſſe of thoſe things which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and ſet before thée in the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and conſidereſt the ampleneſſe of the heauenly gift, thou hungreſt and thirſteſt after righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.6.</note> therefore alſo thou ſhalt bee filled, the ſinnes ſhall not hurt thée,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.20</note> which doe not pleaſe thée: thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt haſte with teares to thy heauenly Father, thou bewaileſt thy ſinnes, and deſireſt that the hunger of thy ſoule may be refreſhed with his heauenly foode: that moſt kinde Father,<note place="margin">verſ. 22.</note> doubt not, will méete thée, hee will kiſſe and receiue thée with ioy, he will giue vnto thée the firſt long garment of innocency, he will cloath thée
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150476:29"/> with the garments of ſaluation, hée will giue thée a ring on thy hand, hée will ſeale thée with his holy ſpirit, hée will giue thée ſhooes for thy féet, he will direct thée in the way of peace and righteouſneſſe, hée will fil thée with the fleſh of that ſacrifice which was ſlaine on the altar of the Croſſe,<note place="margin">verſ. 23.</note> and was offered vnto him for a ſwéet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſauour. Lay aſide therefore all feare of vnworthy eating, he which is moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy in his owne eyes hee is accepted before God: hée that diſpleaſeth himſelfe pleaſeth God: hee that is caſt downe in himſelfe in true contrition of heart, hée againe is raiſed vp by the moſt louing hand of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> The weakeneſſe of Faith.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>FAITH is altogether required to the wholeſome vſe of the Supper, and fruit of the promiſes of the Goſpell, ſeeing the hand of the giuer is not ſufficient to the parricipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of almes, but there muſt of neceſſitie alſo come the hand of the receiuer: but now my faith is weake, the ſhip of my heart bruiſed with diuers ſtormes of tentations, doth oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wauer, and caſtes mee downe from the firmeneſſe of faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>WEake faith notwithſtanding is faith, neither doth faith therefore
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150476:30"/> apprehend Chriſt, and in Chriſt the grace of God, remiſſion of ſinnes, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, becauſe it is ſtrong, but becauſe it is faith: ſtrong faith doth more ſtrongly imbrace Chriſt, neuertheleſſe weake faith alſo doth not reiect Chriſt, but wholeſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehend him. The faithful ſeruant of God, Chriſt our Sauior, doth not breake a bruiſed Réed,<note place="margin">Eſa. 42.2.</note> nor ſmoaking Flaxe hée doth not quench, but he doth moſt benigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue him that is weak in Faith. The leaſt ſparke of faith is the worke of the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.3.</note> becauſe of our ſelues, as it were of our ſelues we cannot ſo much as thinke any thing that is good,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.5.</note> but to will and to performe is of God: therefore God will not deſpiſe his worke,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> which hee hath begunne in thy heart by the holy Ghoſt, but will performe it, and confirme it. Euen as a Mother tendereth her Children,<note place="margin">Eſa. 66.13.</note> ſo God comforteth vs: but now a mother doth far more tenderly handle an Infant, and takes greater care thereof, then of the reſt that are bigge growen: ſo God doth not turne himſelfe away from him that is weake in faith, but endeuours to heale and confirme him as it were a ſicke man. <hi>If you ſhall haue faith as it were a graine of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard ſeed;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 17.20</note> 
                     <hi>and ſhall ſay to this hill, paſſe from hence thither, and it ſhall paſſe, and nothing ſhall be impoſſible vnto you,</hi> ſaith the truth. If miraculous faith can doe ſo much, that it can tranſpoſe hils, if it be ſcarce as big as a graine of Muſtard ſéed, why cannot ſauing faith doe the ſame, that it tranſpoſe the hilles of tentations and doubtings,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150476:30"/> howſoeuer it be very infirme and weake? The power of God is performed in our weakeneſſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9</note> take héede therefore that thou be not caſt downe in thy minde for the weakeneſſe of thy faith. But rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the power of God, God can water that which is drie, heale that which is wounded, bend that which is ſtiffe, cheriſh that which is colde, gouerne that which is out of the way. Acknowledge onely the infirmitie of thy faith, and leane ſo much the ſtronger on the ſtaffe of the word of God, for the word as it is the ſéede, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is it the nouriſhment or foode of faith. Pray with the Diſciples of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Luk. 17.5 Mark. 9.24</note> 
                     <hi>O Lord encreaſe our faith,</hi> and with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the lunaticke childe, <hi>I beleeue Lord, helpe mine vnbeliefe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> The want of the feeling of Faith.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>MY faith is not onely weake, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I doe not feele any faith at all in my heart, neither doe I call vpon God with that heat of the ſpirit which may pierce the clouds. I feare therefore, leaſt then my faith haue periſhed, and be vtterly ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inct; but if my faith be extinct, what hope or ſaluation can there remaine for mee? I proue my ſelfe, and behold I doe not feele faith in my heart, therefore I ſhall be of the number of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:150476:31"/>
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>THe ſpirit helpes our infirmitie, as it were with a hand put vnder, for euen as we know not what we may pray for, or how we ought to pray,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> yet the ſpirit makes interceſſion for vs with ſighes that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be vttered: ſo what or how wée may beléeue ſometimes we doe not féele, but the ſpirit doth cheriſh and conſerue faith in our heart. A ſparke lies ſléeping and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder the aſhes, although outwardly it doth not appeare, ſo faith ſometimes dwels in the innermoſt corners of the heart, although it cannot be felt of vs, therefore from the want of the féeling of faith, thou mayeſt not gather, that thy faith is periſhed and extinct, when as yet thou doeſt deſire, ſigh, and art willing to beléeue, that deſire, that ſighing, that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling doth come from faith. Furthermore, it is one thing not to féele faith, another thing to put away beléeuing; that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to him that wraſtles, this agrées to him that is ſtubbornely rebellious.<note place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> Chriſt dwels altogether by faith in thy heart, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou doeſt not manifeſtly féele that inhabitation of grace, euen as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, that inward Comforter, hath an holy houſe in thine heart, although ſometime he doth with-draw from thée the féeling of that conſolation.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.18</note> As <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of beléeuers beléeued againſt hope in hope, ſo thou oughteſt to relie on the word againſt thine owne ſenſe. As we ought to captiuate all our vnderſtanding
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150476:31"/> vnder the obedience of faith, ſo thou mayeſt alſo captiuate that want of the féeling of faith with faith, that is, thou mayeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the word in thy heart, and cleaue firmely there-vnto. The ſéede lies hidden vnder the clods of earth, although it doth not as yet thruſt forth the blade vtterly: ſo the ſéede of faith lies hid in thy heart, although the fruit thereof as yet doth not fully and plainely appeare. In ſléeping thou doeſt not féele faith, but farre be it from thée that thou ſhouldeſt ſay, that then thy faith is periſhed; ſo in this temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it were a certaine ſléepe, hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt thy ſoule, that thou canſt not féele the mouing of thy faith, but farre be it from thée, that therefore thou ſhouldeſt thinke that thy faith is vtterly extinguiſht.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XX.</hi> The want of power to beleeue.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>TRuly I doe ſigh to my Sauiour, but I doe both feele and grieue that I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue; I would wiſh truly that I might be made partaker of the benefits of Chriſt, but I doe not feele that I can apprehend them by faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>OF thy ſelfe thou canſt not, but on him which ſtrengthens thée, Chriſt, thou canſt doe all things.<note place="margin">Phil. 4 13.</note> God would haue thée altogether, and in earneſt would haue thée to beléeue, for to that end hée offers to thée his word, that through it, by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150476:32"/> of the holy Ghoſt, hée may kindie faith in thy heart, onely doe not thou put away that word, neither reſiſt the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the holy Ghoſt, in ſhort time thou ſhalt féele moſt plentifull fruit of the word. For if God ſeriouſly would haue thée to beléeue, ſurely he will alſo worke in thée that beliefe, if thou doe not reſiſt his will with actuall ſtubbornneſſe. Thou ſayeſt that thou canſt not beléeue, and yet thou art conſtrained to confeſſe, that thou doeſt ſigh vnto Chriſt, and deſire his benefits, that ſame ſighing, that ſame deſiring is the beginning of faith. The holy Ghoſt will bring to paſſe, will ſurely bring to paſſe that worke of faith, which hée hath begun in thée; take héede onely that thou doe not put by his wholſome operation. Thou oughteſt not to reſolue, that the ſenſe and mouing of faith kindled in thy heart, is firſt to be expected, before that thou wilt heare, meditate, and receiue the word of the Goſpell. This is a peruerſe opinion, which take héede that thou ſucke not in, that thou put not vpon thée: this is a peruerſe order, which take héede, that thou doe not follow. In the Schoole of the holy Ghoſt wée muſt take our begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the hearing and meditation of the word, by that meanes thou art brought vnto faith, by faith vnto the féeling of faith. Thou ſayeſt that thou canſt not beléeue, therefore thou oughteſt to heare the word, meditate on it, and receiue it into thy heart, that thou mayeſt beléeue. GOD giues his holy ſpirit to thoſe that<note place="margin">Luk. 11.13</note>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150476:32"/> aſke, and yet without the grace of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt we cannot aſke: ſo God giues faith to them that ſigh after it, and yet without the beginning of faith we cannot ſigh after it. For a ſurety faith riſeth with a certaine wraſtling in the heart, it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed with wraſtling, it is performed in the heart with wraſtling, and that which we cannot doe of our ſelues, wée are able to doe by his gift, which hath ſaid: <hi>No man commeth vnto mee, vnleſſe the Father draw him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.44.</note> 
                     <hi>Euery one that heareth of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and learneth, he commeth vnto me, him that commeth vnto me, I will not caſt forth.</hi> If thou art not yet drawne, pray that thou mayeſt be drawne: heare and learne, that thou mayeſt come vnto Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXI.</hi> The ſmall number of good workes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>TRue and liuely faith alwaies workes by loue, on the other ſide that faith which hath not workes, is dead in it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> As the body without the ſoule is dead ſo faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out workes is dead.<note place="margin">Iac. 2.17. Verſ. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Rom. 9.21 Verſ. 18.</note> But now I doe not ſee a great number of good workes, which may giue manifeſt teſtimonie of my faith. Euill cleaues vnto me, that am willing to doe good, to will is preſent with mee, but I finde no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to performe that which is good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>THou doeſt well, that thou doeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeme the light of faith, out of the beames of good workes. For as workes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150476:33"/> which are not done of faith, are not truly good workes: ſo faith which is without workes is not true faith, but a vaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion,<note place="margin">Math. 7.16</note> and emptie ſhadow. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10</note> ſaith our Sauiour; <hi>Doe your endeauour,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter, that you may make your calling and election ſure.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of workes we muſt iudge of faith, and this is the third property of faith, that as it hath contrition to vſher it, and true confidence on Chriſt in ſtead of an Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall forme, ſo it alwaies hath new obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to follow it. Therefore thou doeſt well, as I haue ſaid, that thou doeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeme the light of faith, out of the beames of good workes, but take héede thou doe not thinke, that thoſe are onely good workes, which are great in their outward ſhew in the eyes of men, and frée from all ſpot of ſinne cleauing vnto them. Vnder the name of good workes is eſpecially vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the inward renuing of the heart, and the kindling of thoſe ſpirituall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the hearts of the regenerate by the holy Ghoſt. Therefore an holy cogitation, a good purpoſe, the true feare of God, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere loue, ardent inuocation are truly good workes, although they are not perceiued and ſéene of men.<note place="margin">Pſa. 45.14</note> The glory of the Kings daughter is within, the outward workes doe giue teſtimonie of that inward glory of the reuelation. Therefore if thou haſt nothing elſe that thou canſt offer vnto God, offer vnto God a good will, and an holy purpoſe to liue godlily. Offer to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150476:33"/> God thy heart, and thou haſt offered all things. Submit thy ſelfe wholy to the will of GOD, cleaue vnto him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne thy will to him, and thou ſhalt be one ſpirit with him.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.17</note> This if thou ſhalt doe, the outward workes will readily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, becauſe the ſpirit of God dwelling in thée, will driue thée to all manner of good workes, but where there is not an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward faculty of working, there the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward good will to God ſufficeth. Neither is there any reaſon why thou ſhouldeſt hope that thou canſt be frée from the ſpot of all infirmitie in this life. Our workes doe pleaſe God, not becauſe they are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely perfect, but becauſe they doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede out of true faith in Chriſt, and are offered of beloued Sonnes in ſtead of a ſacrifice of thankeſgiuing. Acknowledge therefore the teſtimonie of good workes which they giue of faith, leaſt thou be caſt downe in thy minde, acknowledge the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of the ſame, and the ſpot of ſin cleauing vnto them, leaſt thou be too much lifted vp in thy minde.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> The want of Merits.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>IVſt is God, and iuſt are his iudgements, therefore hee will giue to none the reward of eternall life, vnleſſe there goe before the merit of good workes. What therefore is my hope, what is my confidence, when my workes are imperfect, foule, many wayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamined, and no way meritorious?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:150476:34"/>
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 6 23 Bern. <hi>Ser.</hi> 1 <hi>in Annunc. Col.</hi> 106.</note>NAy, eternall life is not the due wages of our deſerts, but the frée gift of God in Chriſt and for Chriſt. For neither are the merits of men ſuch, that for them eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life is due of right, and God ſhould doe iniurie to ſome man, vnleſſe he ſhould giue him it. For that I may not ſpeake of this, that all merits are the gifts of God, and ſo man is more a debter vnto God for them, then God to man, what are al merits to ſo great glory? All the Saints do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,<note place="margin">Exod. 34.7. Eſa. 64.6.</note> that before God no man is innocent, that all their righteouſneſſes are before God like the cloath of a menſtruous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that no man can ſtand before the iudgement of God, if he will impute ſins, that when they haue done all things that are commanded of God,<note place="margin">Pſa. 130.3. Luk. 17.10</note> they are neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe vnprofitable ſeruants, what place therefore can there be héere for merits? who can preſume of ſufficiencie to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either of his owne wiſedome or righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes or holines?<note place="margin">Bern <hi>Serm.</hi> 22. <hi>in cant. Col.</hi> 555. Gerſon <hi>li.</hi> 4. <hi>de conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. Theolog. proſ.</hi> 1. Rom. 8.18</note> who can ſhew his owne righteouſneſſes as it were in boaſting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, more then a woman the cloath of her confuſion to a man? neither our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings nor our ſufferings are worthie of the future glory which ſhalbe reuealed on vs.</p>
                  <p>We cannot deſerue that cruſt of bread which we eate, by our obedience, but are conſtrained to begge it by daily Prayers, of God, how much more incomparably leſſe can we deſerue the reward of eternall life by our merits? Therefore if thou wilt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150476:34"/> fall from grace, bragge of thy merits.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in Pſ. <hi>31.</hi> Id. de verb. Apoſt. Ser. <hi>15. Fulgen. 1.</hi> ad momin. pag. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </note> God giues altogether fréely, ſaues altogether fréely, becauſe he findes nothing for which to ſaue, and hée findes much for which to damne. Of grace is giuen not onely to the iuſtified good life, but alſo to the glorified eternall life: and therefore death is ſaid to be wages, but eternall life is ſaid to be grace, becauſe that is rendred as due, this is giuen as frée.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bern.</hi> Ser. innat. Mar. Col. <hi>213.</hi>
                     </note> Therefore let another ſéeke for merit, doe thou ſtudie to finde grace, let the mercie of the Lord be thy merit, thou art not plainely poore in merit, as long as he is not wanting mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.<note place="margin">Serm. <hi>67.</hi> in Cant.</note> There is no place for grace to enter where merit hath alreadie taken vp the roome, Thou doeſt detract from grace, whatſoeuer thou doeſt depute vnto merit. It ſufficeth to merit,<note place="margin">Serm. <hi>68.</hi> in Cant.</note> to know that merit doth not ſuffice. Place all thy confidence altogether on God. Embrace his mercie, ſéeke thy merits in the wounds of Chriſt, &amp; thou ſhalt not haue any want of merits.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIII.</hi> The accuſation of the Law.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Acknowledge our works not to be merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, neither to appeaſe God, but that out of faith they may pleaſe him. And how can they chuſe but diſpleaſe him, when they are not perfectly conformable to the law of God. The law is an eternall &amp; vnchangeable rule of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, condemning all whatſoeuer is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable there-vnto. Therefore the dart of damnation is ſhaken againſt me, &amp; my works, vnleſſe thou ſhew me, what ſhield I may op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:150476:35"/>
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note>CHriſt hath redeemed thée from the curſe of the Law, being made a curſe for thee, Curſed is euery one that hangeth on the wood. When the fulneſſe of time came,<note place="margin">Cap 4.4.</note> God ſent his owne Sonne, borne of a woman, made vnder the Law, that he might redeeme thoſe which were vnder the Law,<note place="margin">Ver. 5. Rom. 10.4. Cap. 8.1.</note> that we might receiue the adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sonnes. The end and fulfilling of the Law is Chriſt to righteouſnes to euery one that beleeueth: Therefore there is no damnation to thée and all, which are by faith in Chriſt, and walke not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh,<note place="margin">Verſ 2. Verſ. 3.</note> there is no feare of the Law, the Law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Ieſus, hath fréed thée from the Law of ſinne and death. For that which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to the Law, becauſe it was made weake through the fleſh, that hath GOD performed,<note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> ſending his Sonne in the likeneſſe of the fleſh of ſinne, and by ſinne condemned ſinne in the fleſh, that the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of the Law might be fulfilled in vs, which walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit. Therefore if by true faith thou doeſt apply the benefits of Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſelfe, there is no cauſe that thou ſhouldeſt feare the curſe of the Lawe. <hi>The ſting of Death is ſinne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55 56.</note> 
                     <hi>the ſtrength of ſinne is the Law, but thankes be vnto God, which hath giuen vs victorie through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord:</hi> Hee hath ouercome our death by his death, hee hath ſatiſfied for our ſinnes by his Paſſion, and hée hath
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150476:35"/> moſt perfectly fulfilled the Law in our ſtead, by his moſt holy obedience. Neither yet is there an aboliſhment of the Law made, but a tranſlation onely. Neither do the Law and the Goſpell deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues mutually, ſéeing the Law is not againſt the promiſes of God,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.21.</note> but is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by faith.</p>
                  <p>For what the Law doth require of vs,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.31</note> that the Goſpell doth tell vs was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of Chriſt in our ſteade. What the Law commands, this Chriſt obtaines. The Law condemneth ſinne, and vs for ſinne, Chriſt doth performe ſatiſfaction for ſinnes, and giues his righteouſneſſe vnto vs. The Law therefore is ſatiſfied by the obedience of Chriſt, becauſe it is perfect: Againe, that fulfilling of the Law through Chriſt, is performed for vs to good becauſe it is not due.<note place="margin">Chyt. li. <hi>1.</hi> de vita et morte, p. <hi>43.</hi>
                     </note> Therefore as thou oughteſt not to behold death in thine owne body, but in Chriſt raiſed vp againe, the conquerour of death, and the giuer of life and ſaluation eternall: ſinne not in thine owne conſcience, but in Chriſt the Lambe of God, bearing and taking away thy ſinnes, and the ſinnes of the whole world: hell and the tentations of being euerlaſtingly caſt away, not in thy ſelfe, and in that innumerable multitude of the damned, but in Chriſt ſuſtaining on the Croſſe, and ouer-comming for vs the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of being caſt away: ſo thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to behold the Law not as it is written in thy hart, but as it is fulfilled by Chriſt, and with him faſtned to the Croſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:150476:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIIII.</hi> The accuſation of Conſcience.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>MY conſcience doth witneſſe, together with the accuſation of the Law, that as an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt iudge riſeth vp againſt mee,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> hom. <hi>64.</hi> in Gen.</note> and is an accuſer of mee, while no man reproues mee, or brings any thing forth againſt mee. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape that domeſticall iudgement ſeate: In this great volumne I ſee and altogether tremble at all my ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nazian.</hi> orat. <hi>26. Bern.</hi> de conuerſ. ad Cler. c. <hi>3.</hi> Col. <hi>114</hi>
                     </note> written with the ſtile of truth: wretch that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this Court of iudgement, in which the ſame is the guiltie, the pleader, the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the iudge, the torturer, the ſcourge, the executioner, the hangman?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.20.</note>IF thy heart doth condemne thée, yet God is greater then thy heart. If the memory of thy faults paſſed, doth accuſe and torment thée, yet Chriſt the Redéemer, which hath ſatiſfied for thy ſinnes, is a mightier,<note place="margin">Col. 2.14.</note> he abſolues thée, frées thée, and ſaues thée. Hee indéed hath blotted out that hand-writing which was written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and was contrary to vs, hee hath taken it cleane away, and hath faſtned it with him to the Croſſe. By the nailes of Chriſt crucified is that accuſing hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of thy conſcience together faſtened, that it is of no force and validitie before God;<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> for being iuſtified by faith, thou haſt peace with GOD, peace of conſcience,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150476:36"/> quietnes of hart, and the moſt bleſſed tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie of the ſoule, which Chriſt the conquerour of ſinne, death and Satan, hath brought backe with him from the graue, and giuen the ſame to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Therefore,<note place="margin">Bern. de conuer. cap. <hi>6.</hi> col. <hi>415.</hi>
                     </note> if thou féeleſt the worme of conſcience, thou oughteſt to ſtrangle him forthwith in this life preſent, not che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh him to immortalitie, for a putrified conſcience begets the immortall wormes.</p>
                  <p>Strangle therefore the worme of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience by ſerious repentance, pray to God for reſt of the heart, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and take héed of the new wounds of conſcience, <hi>that is,</hi> the worſt relapſe of ſinnes. In this life there is as yet a time of pardon, a time of grace, a time of quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the conſcience. In this life the booke of conſcience may as yet be amended out of the booke of life,<note place="margin">Apoc. 20.12.</note> but in the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the bookes ſhall be opened, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe alſo the booke of conſcience, in which, before the whole world, grauen with great letters, ſhall all the particular faults and offences of men be ſéene, which are not blotted out in this life by true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, by faith, and amendement of life. Before that day of iudgement come, and the time of grace paſſe away, thou mayeſt haue as yet excellent hope and ſure confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> which through the eternall ſpirit, hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelfe without ſpot to God, will clenſe thy conſcience from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:150476:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXV.</hi> Too late Repentance.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>TRuly, I am earneſtly ſorry for ſo many wounds inflicted on my conſcience; I doe earneſtly deſire the cure of my wounds, I haue an earneſt deſire to keepe a good conſcience hereafter, but I feare leſt that my repentance be too late: I feare, leſt the grace of God ſo oftimes reiected of mee, doe againe reiect and forſake mee.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de verâ &amp; falſâ poenit. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </note> Late repentance is wont to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue many, and that repentance which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a dying man, hee muſt feare, leſt that alſo dye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>NAy, there is nothing too late which is true and earneſt.<note place="margin">Cyprian. tract. <hi>1.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Demet.</note> No repentance is to late for him that abides yet in this world; there are ſome which are called, and come at the eleuenth houre of the day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lords Vineyard,<note place="margin">Mat. 20.9.</note> and receiue the reward of Grace. No length of time doth preiudicate eyther Gods equitie or his pietie.<note place="margin">Fulgent. Epiſt. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> Repentance is neuer too late with GOD <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in whoſe ſight aſwell the things paſt, as the things to come, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes held for preſent. Behold the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Thiefe on the croſſe, which confeſſing Chriſt with his mouth, vpon whoſe vtmoſt lippes, as it were, his ſoule dwelt, ready to depart, gods the pardon of his ſinnes, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>miſe of the heauenly paradiſe. As long as that to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150476:37"/> day is named,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.13.</note> ſo long God doth earneſtly looke for our conuerſion. As long as the heauenly Bridegroome doth as yet defer his comming,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.5.</note> ſo long the gate of Grace and indulgence, doth as yet lye open: The whole time of our life, yea the laſt houre thereof is graunted vs to the ſpace of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.<note place="margin">Eſa. 65.2.</note> God ſpreads forth his hands all day, neyther doth hee caſt forth him that comes vnto him at what time ſoeuer hee come.<note place="margin">Iohn 6.37.</note> Therefore take thou care of that, that thy repentance be true and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and then thou néedeſt not feare, leſt it be too late. If when the houre of death drawes néere, thou therfore repenteſt thée, becauſe thou art deſtituted of the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſinning, that repentance is falſe, for by this reaſon thou doeſt not leaue thy ſinnes, but thy ſinnes forſake thée. If thou therefore repenteſt becauſe thou ſéeſt the puniſhment of thy ſinnes neare; that repentance is likewiſe falſe, for it procéeds out of the loue of thy ſelfe, not out of the ſincere loue of God: it procéeds not out of the hate of ſinne, but out of the irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe of moſt iuſt puniſhment. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that thou mayeſt repent truly and earneſtly, grieue for thy ſins ſo often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and therefore grieue, becauſe thou haſt ſo often &amp; ſo grieuouſly by them offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded God the chiefeſt good, ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e in Chriſt the remiſſion of thy ſins, and ſeriouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to thy ſelfe, whatſoeuer ſhall remaine of thy life, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it out wholly on the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, ſubmit thy ſelfe to God: &amp; be humbled from thy heart before him: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150476:38"/> it to his will, what and how great pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, a thouſand times deſerued of thée, he will inflict vpon thée, that it may appeare that thou doeſt repent out of the hatred of ſinne, and not out of the hatred of puniſhment.<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.19</note> Such a contrite and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled heart will be a moſt acceptable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vnto God, for ſo he ſaith by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,<note place="margin">Eſa. 66.2.</note> 
                     <hi>To whom ſhall I haue reſpect, but to the poore and contrite in ſpirit, and him that trembles at my words?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVI.</hi> The doubting of the grace of God.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>TRuly I feele in my heart ſerious contrition and griefe for my ſinnes, neither doe I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together deſpaire of the mercy of God, yet my heart is ſhaken with the waues of doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, neither as yet am I certainely aſſured of the free remiſſion of my ſinnes. Indeed, well I hope, in the meane time humbly I doubt the conſideration of Gods mercy doth lift me vp, but the thought of mine owne vnworthineſſe doth againe caſt me downe. I am conuerted vnto God, therefore I hope well, but I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted too late, therefore I doubt as yet in part.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>BVt I will ſet moſt firme props vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy wauering faith, on which thou mayeſt relie thée againſt all the tempeſts of doubtings: for neither is that doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an humble confeſſion of our vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, but a dangerous oppugning of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150476:38"/> the faith that ought of right to be giuen to Gods promiſes: neither is there any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of doubting of ſufficient ſtrength in late conuerſion and repentance, when the mercy of God doth offer to al that are ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly conuerted a moſt certaine promiſe of the remiſſion of ſins. Firſt of al, therefore, attend to the vnmoueable verity of the promiſes of God. Whoſoeuer they are that acknowledging and bewailing their ſins, doe ſéeke remiſſion of them in Chriſt, and conceiue a firme purpoſe of amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, to them God hath promiſed his grace, forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. <hi>Whoſoeuer beleeueth on the Sonne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 13.15 18. 1 Ioh. 5.12 Mar. 16.16</note> 
                     <hi>doth not periſh, but hath life eternall. He that beleeueth on him, is not iudged. He that hath the Sonne, the ſame alſo hath eternall life. Hee that ſhall beleeue, and be baptized, ſhall be ſaued.</hi> He that hath promiſed theſe things is God, whoſe word is more firme then heauen &amp; earth, which is the truth it ſelfe,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.11</note> which is faithfull, and cannot deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe or his word. That therefore which God offers with indubitate promiſes, that muſt thou entertain with indubitate faith: neither muſt thou pretend the infirmitie of thy nature, which cannot imbrace the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, with ſuch an aſſurance of truſt, for this fault of thy nature muſt be corrected by the efficacy of the holy ſpirit. As thou doſt not beléeue on CHRIST out of the ſtrength of nature, but out of the working of the Holy Ghoſt: ſo by the grace of the ſame ſpirit thou mayeſt be aſſured of the mercy of the Heauenly
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150476:39"/> Father againſt all doubting that is inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in thy depriued nature.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues not God makes him a liar.</hi> Aſmuch as thou doubteſt, ſo much is diminiſhed of thy truſt, therefore thou muſt reſiſt that doubting, neither is that to be ſet forth vnder the ſpecious name of humilitie: ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, Humilitie ought to ariſe out of the conſideration of our vnworthineſſe: in the meane time, out of the meditation of the promiſes of God, ought there neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe a firme confidence to ariſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath comfort from the hidden ſeat of his maieſty, and hath manifeſted his will in his word, that wee might bee ſure of his will.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, God hath promulged not onely legall promiſes, which haue added vnto them the condition of perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and therefore to vs are made vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, but alſo Euangelicall, which are frée, that with firme confidence of heart we might relye vpon them.<note place="margin">Rom 4.16</note> Therefore of faith fréely, ſayth the Apoſtle, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe may bee firme.<note place="margin">Pſa. 116.11</note> Mens promiſes are vncertaine and doubtfull, becauſe euery man is a lyar, but the promiſes of God are certaine and vnmoueable, becauſe God is truth it ſelfe. As God is true in threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, ſo is he alſo in promiſing. As with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt certaine damnation doth hang ouer al vnbeléeuing impenitent perſons, ſo in Chriſt certaine ſaluation is propoſed to all that are conuerted vnto God and belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.<note place="margin">Cypr. ſerm. <hi>4.</hi> de morta. pa. <hi>209.</hi>
                     </note> Doeſt thou doubt that theſe things will come to paſſe, which God promiſeth,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150476:39"/> which is true, whoſe word is eternall and firm to them that beléeue. If a graue &amp; lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable man ſhould promiſe thée any thing, thou wouldſt put truſt in his promiſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wouldſt thou thinke that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be deceiued of him whom thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt know to be conſtant in his words &amp; doings. Now God ſpeaketh with thée, and doeſt thou perfideouſly wauer in thine incredulous minde? Furthermore, attend to the ſtabilitie of the oath of GOD: <hi>I liue,</hi> ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.11</note> 
                     <hi>I will not the death of a ſinner, but that hee may be conuerted and liue. Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you,</hi> ſayth Chriſt, <hi>hee which heares my word,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 5.25.</note> 
                     <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues on him, which ſent mee, hath life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but hath paſſed from death to life. Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you, if any man keepe my word, hee ſhall not ſee death for euer.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</note> This hath God ſayd, this hath hee promiſed, if that be little, hee hath ſworne it:<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>88.</hi>
                     </note> Bleſſed therefore we, for whoſe ſakes God ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, but O moſt wretched if we do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue GOD then when hee ſweareth.<note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de poeniten.</note> Acknowledge therefore the wonderfull and neuer ſufficiently praiſed mercy of God, that he willing to ſhew more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to the heires of the promiſe the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutabilitie and immobilitie of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, hath added an oath,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.71.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">verſ. 18.</note> that by two vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable things (for it cannot come to paſſe that God ſhould lye) we might haue moſt ſtrong comfort, which haue fled to lay hold on the hope that is ſet before vs.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:150476:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVII.</hi> The want of due preparation.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>ALL theſe things doe eaſily perſwade with me, that I doe not doubt of the firmenes of the promiſes of God in themſelues: in the meane time I am yet vncertaine, whether they be ſo firme and vnmoueable to me, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am in the number of them to whom God doth promiſe and offer ſo great things.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>NAy, but becauſe God promiſeth theſe things to all that flye vnto Chriſt with true repentance and faith:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.13.</note> therefore alſo he promiſeth them to thée, ſéeing thou alſo beléeueſt in Chriſt. Attend therefore farther to the inward ſealing of the holy Ghoſt: for the ſpirit doth not only teſtifie outwardly in the word, but alſo inwardly in thine heart.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> The ſpirit it ſelfe giues te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie to thy ſpirit that thou art the ſon of God,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> therefore alſo an heyre. Thou haſt receiued the ſpirit which is of God, that thou mayeſt know the things which are giuen to thée of God. He which doth confirme and ſtrengthen thée with all that are truly godly in Chriſt, and hee which hath annoynted thée is God: which hath alſo ſigned thée, and confirmed thée as it were, with his ſeale, and giuen the earneſt of the ſpirit in thy heart. Becauſe thou art the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.12</note> therefore God hath ſent the ſpirit of his ſonne into thine hart, crying, <hi>Abba Father.</hi> Beléeuing the word of truth, and the Goſpell of ſaluation, thou
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150476:40"/> art ſealed by the holy ſpirit of promiſe,<note place="margin">Cap. 4.30.</note> which is the earneſt of thine inheritance for the purchaſed redemption, by which thou art ſealed againſt the day of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Euen as the Bridegroome which hath giuen the promiſe of marriage to the Bride, giues her an earneſt, which is a pledge of the marriage to come: ſo God hath eſpouſed or betroathed himſelf to thée in faith:<note place="margin">Oſe. 2.19.</note> he hath betroathed himſelfe to thée in mercy,<note place="margin">Apoc. 19.7</note> but as yet the marriage of the Lambe doth not appeare: therefore hee giues vnto thée the earneſt of his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, by which thou mayſt be confirmed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fulfilling of the promiſes, and the leading to the heauenly marriage which is to come. This is the ſpirit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, becauſe it doth witnes that thou art adopted for the Son of God. This is that ſeale by which the promiſes of God are ſealed in thy heart: this is that earneſt by which the word of trueth is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto thée.<note place="margin">1 Iohn 4.13.</note> By this thou knoweſt that thou abideſt in God and God in thée, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath giuen to thée of his ſpirit.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVIII.</hi> The doubting of the inhabitation of the holy Ghoſt.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>BVT from whence may I be certaine that my heart is the temple and houſe of the holy Ghoſt? the ſpots of ſinne do cleaue vnto me, and I feele that in my fleſh dwels no good, how therefore ſhall that holy Spirit, which is holyneſſe and puritie it ſelfe dwell in mee?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:150476:41"/>
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.23</note>WE receiue the firſt fruits of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit onely in this life, wee expect the full meaſure and perfect tenths hereafter in the life eternall, there remaines in this life the wraſtling of the fleſh and the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.14</note> we remaine as yet in part carnall, and ſold vnder ſinne; yet neuertheleſſe, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of regeneration and renouation, wée are temples of the Holy Ghoſt. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, from thence thou mayeſt know, that the Spirit of God dwels in thée, becauſe thou doſt bewaile and deteſt thy ſins,<note place="margin">Sapi. 1.4. 2 Cor. 4.13.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that holy Spirit dwels not in the body, ſubiect vnto ſinne, becauſe thou doſt beléeue on Chriſt, and loueſt him, for it is the ſpirit of faith, becauſe thou calleſt vpon God the moſt benigne Father with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſighes,<note place="margin">Zach. 13.9</note> for it is the ſpirit of grace and prayers, and crieth in the hearts of the godly,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Abba Father:</hi> becauſe thou art led with the deſire of all good, for they that are the temples of the holy Ghoſt, are led by him, ſurely to good; becauſe thou oft times doſt féele a foretaſte of eternall life in thy heart,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.14</note> 
                     <hi>for the kingdome of God is not meat and drinke,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> 
                     <hi>but righteouſneſſe, peace and ioy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Wherefore, if thy ſoule hath ſometimes felt in the ſecret of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience the ſpirit of the Son,<note place="margin">Ber in Can. ſerm <hi>8.</hi> col. <hi>509.</hi>
                     </note> crying <hi>Abba Father,</hi> let her preſume that ſhe is beloued with a fatherly affection, when ſhee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues that ſhee is affected with the ſame ſpirit, with which is alſo the ſonne. In the ſpirit of the Son ſhée may know her ſelfe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150476:41"/> to be daughter of the Father, &amp; the ſpouſe and ſiſter of the ſonne. And although all theſe things are ſometime weake and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, yet be not out of heart, but aſke for increaſe of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.13</note> for God will giue this ſpirit to thoſe that aſke him. Stir vp the gift,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.6</note> that frée and gracious gift of the ſpirit which is in thée, that is, by aſking, by ſéeking, by knocking, by meditating on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> word, by reſiſting euill concupiſcences. There is here no perfection, but a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all way to perfection. Beſide this inward ſeale and teſtimony of the holy ſpirit, God hath giuen thée the Sacraments, which are the ſeales of the heauenly promiſes, the waggons of the benefits of Chriſt, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them vnto thée, and the meanes of the begetting, cheriſhing, &amp; confirming of thy faith, that thou mayſt be ſure that the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of Chriſt doe pertaine in ſpeciall vnto thée:<note place="margin">Cypr ſerm. de mort. pa. <hi>209.</hi>
                     </note> Thou wert receiued into the Church by baptiſme, and fed in the Lords Supper with the body &amp; blood of Chriſt: being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by theſe ſeales, beléeue the word of the Goſpell ſurely and without all doubt. Why doeſt thou doubt? why doeſt thou wauer? this is that God ſhould not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be, this is to offend Chriſt the Maſter of beléeuers, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſin of incredulity, this is, for him that is placed in the Church, not to haue faith in the houſe of faith. Attend moreouer to the infallibility of the promiſed hearing. God hath promiſed euen with an oath put thereto, that he wil heare our prayers, &amp; that whatſoeuer we aſke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will ſhall be giuen vnto vs:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150476:42"/> 
                     <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>whatſoeuer yee ſhall aske the Father in my name,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.23 Mat. 18.19</note> 
                     <hi>hee will giue vnto you. If two of you ſhall conſent vpon earth on any manner of thing, whatſoeuer they ſhal aske, it ſhal be done to them of my Father, which is in heauen. This is the truſt which we haue vnto God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.14</note> 
                     <hi>if we aske according to his will, we ſhal obtaine it.</hi> The very ſame which hath promiſed hearing, hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded vs to aſke forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenes of ſins: therfore what place of doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting will there remaine of the remiſſion of ſins? how ſhould Chriſt haue commanded to ioyne to prayer the word <hi>Amen,</hi> if hee would haue had vs to doubt of hearing?</p>
                  <p>To conclude, attend to the property of true faith, as by which we haue acceſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that grace wherein we ſtand, and glory of the hope of glory,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note> promiſed of God, through which wee come with truſt vnto the throne of grace, that wee may attaine mercy, and finde grace, through which we are kept by the power of God vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.5.</note> through which we know that we are tranſlated from death to life:<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.14</note> through which wee are moſt certainly perſwaded, that neither death,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38</note> nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent,<note place="margin">verſ. 39.</note> nor things to come, neither height, nor depth, nor any other creature, can ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>148.</hi>
                     </note> Weighing all theſe things, let thy frailtie lift it ſelfe vp, let it not deſpaire, let it not bruiſe it ſelfe, let it not turne it ſelfe away. Chriſt hath promiſed thée, that thou ſhalt bee there
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150476:42"/> where hée is. What hath God promiſed vnto thée O mortall man? that thou ſhalt liue for euer. Doeſt thou not beléeue? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, beléeue, it is more now which hée hath done, then what he hath promiſed: What hath he done? he hath died for thée: What hath he promiſed? that thou ſhalt liue with him: it is more incredible that the eternal hath died, then that the mortal can liue for eternitie. Now thou holdeſt that which is more incredible, why doeſt thou doubt of that which remaines? God hath promiſed thée heauen, he hath giuen thée his Son, which is a greater gift then hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIX.</hi> The doubting of perſeuerance.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>TRuly I doe nothing doubt, but that by my Mediator Chriſt, there lyes open to me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to GOD; I ſurely truſt that I am in the grace of God, yet I cannot but doubt of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance.<note place="margin">Matth. 10.22. cap. 24. v. 46.</note> I know that it is perſeuerance alone that is crowned, I heare that they onely, which ſhall perſeuere to the end ſhall be ſaued. Not to haue begun well, but to goe through well is the part of vertue.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug.</hi> Ser. <hi>8</hi> ad frat. in Erem. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro. in Epiſt. ad furiam. Theol. myſt. Harp. c. <hi>34.</hi>
                     </note> Neither is the beginning but the end required in Chriſtians. <hi>Iudas</hi> began well, but he ended ill; <hi>Paul</hi> began ill, but hee ended well. Without perſeuerance neither he that fighteth obtaineth victory, nor the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour the palme. I heare the ouer-ſeer and appointer of our maſteries crying: hold that which thou haſt, leaſt another take thy crown. I heare and I feare, I feare and I doubt:<note place="margin">Apoc. 3.12</note> I doubt and I caſt away the confidence of my heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:150476:43"/>
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bern.</hi> Serm. <hi>3.</hi> de ſep. frag. miſer. Col. <hi>183.</hi>
                     </note>COnſider thrée things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n which thy whole hope doth conſiſt, the charity of the adoption, the truth of the promiſe, the power of performance. Now let thy fooliſh thought murmure as much as it will, ſaying? who art thou, and how great is that glory, or by what merits hopeſt thou to obtaine it? and doe thou anſwere confidently: I know whom I haue belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and I am ſure that in the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his charitie he hath adopted me, that he is true in his promiſe, that hée is powerfull in performance. This is the thrée-fold cord, which is not eaſily bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, which I pray thée, that thou holde firmely faſt, being let downe to thée out of our Country, euen into this dungeon, that it may lift thée vp, that it may draw thée euen to the beholding and ſight of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the great God. This is the moſt firme Anker of thy hope, theſe are thoſe thrée pillars on which thou mayeſt relie againſt the flouds &amp; ſtormes of doubtings, that is to ſay, the good will of God adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, his ſure faithfulneſſe promiſing, and his infinite power to fulfill his promiſes. The good GOD hath promiſed good things,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> hée hath begun to worke a good worke in thée, hée that hath begun will performe it, according to his good liking. The good GOD hath promiſed good things,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.15.</note> he that hath promiſed is faithfull and true, he will not ſuffer thée to be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue thy ſtrength, but will giue an
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150476:43"/> iſſue with the temptation, that thou mayeſt be able to beare it.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.12</note> The good God hath promiſed God things, he that hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed is able to fulfill his promiſes, Therefore be thou ſure that he can kéepe that which is committed vnto him, euen vnto that day of iudgement.<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.28 Verſ. 29.</note> No man ſhal ſnatch the ſhéepe of Chriſt out of his hands, the heauenly Father, which hath deliuered them to the Sonne, is greater then all, and no man can ſnatch them out of the hand of the Father.<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.20</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt the onely high Prieſt of the new Teſtament hath aſkt for all, which were to beléeue on him, through the word, that they may be with him, and may ſée the glory that is giuen to him of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.10</note> Wherefore ſéeing thou doeſt beléeue on Chriſt, thou haſt the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of God in thine owne ſelfe, that Chriſt hath alſo aſkt for thée: how then canſt thou doubt that that prayer is heard of the heauenly Father?<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.18. Math. 3.17 Heb. 5.7.</note> Should not the Sonne which is in the boſome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be heard of the Father? Should the Sonne in whom the Father is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, be put backe with his prayers? farre be this away, farre be it, nay rather in the dayes of his fleſh, offering prayers and ſupplications with ſtrong crying &amp; teares to his Father, he was heard for the thing that hée feared. Therefore Chriſt hath aſkt for thée, hée hath aſkt and hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that in time to come thou mayeſt liue with him, partaker of the heauenly glory.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:150476:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXX.</hi> The ſleights and ſtrength of Satan.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Hope truly that I ſhall be conſerued as a faithfull ſheepe in the hand of my Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, yet in the meane time I feare the lying in waite of Satan,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> which like the infernall Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on compaſſeth, ſeeking whom hee may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure; I feare his ſtrength, ſeeing he is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, in boldneſſe moſt readie, in ſtrength moſt ſtrong, in ſleights moſt cunning, in diligence and ſwiftneſſe infatigable, moſt full of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, moſt quicke and nimble in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of fighting: how ſhall I be able to take heede of his ſnares, and to eſcape his ſtrength? Sometimes hee doth impugne and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute me openly and violently, ſometimes hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly and fraudulently, but alwaies maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and cruelly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.28</note>
                     <hi>NO man</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ſhall ſnatch my ſheepe out of my hands:</hi> therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that infernall Wolfe, although hée be euery way furniſhed with ſleights and ſtrength.<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.29</note> The Prince of this world came, and he had not any thing in Chriſt: therefore neither in them, which are by faith in Chriſt, and in whoſe hearts Chriſt dwelleth by faith,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> ſhall hée haue any thing at all. It is Chriſt, which fighteth for thée, and in thée, beléeue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, the Diuell ſhall not be ſtronger then he.<note place="margin">Math. 4.2.</note> Chriſt was tempted of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and ouercame him valiantly, the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150476:44"/> victorie of the Lord is the triumph of the ſeruants.<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> By his death Chriſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed him which had the power of death, that is, the Diuell: hée hath ſpoiled the Principalities, and hath made a ſhew of the powers, openly, confidently,<note place="margin">Col. 2.15.</note> triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer them in himſelfe: as it were an heauenly <hi>Dauid,</hi> he hath ouercome the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall <hi>Goliah,</hi> with the ſword of the Croſſe: this fight of Chriſt, this victorie is healthfull to the whole Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this is the Song of conqueſt and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant verſe.<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.10.</note> Now is there made ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and ſtrength, and the Kingdome of our God, and the power of his Chriſt: becauſe the accuſer of our brethren is caſt forth, which did accuſe them, before the ſight of our GOD, day and night.<note place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> And they haue ouercome him by the blood of the Lambe, and by the word of their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie.<note place="margin">Iac. 4.7.</note> Therefore let all the aſſurance of thy truſt, and boaſting of thy hope, be in this victorie of Chriſt. Reſiſt the Diuell in the power of Chriſt, and hée will flye away from thée:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ber.</hi> in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatio de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotiſ. c. <hi>14.</hi> Col. <hi>1205.</hi>
                     </note> As often as thou reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, thou ouercommeſt the Diuell, thou makeſt glad the Angels, thou glorifieſt God; for he exhorts thée to fight, he helps thée to ouercome he beholds thée ſtriuing in the battaile, he lifts thée vp when thou doeſt faint, hée crownes thée when thou doeſt ouercome:<note place="margin">Gregor. Nyſſen. <hi>li. de Beatit. p.</hi> 68. Eph. 6.10.</note> hée is the Chiefetaine and Gouernour of thoſe that ſtriue, and the Crowne of thoſe that doe triumph. Be thou ſtrengthened therefore in the Lord, and in the power of his might.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150476:45"/> 
                     <hi>Put on the whole Armour of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 11. Verſ. 12. Verſ. 13. Verſ. 14. Verſ. 15. Verſ. 16. Verſ. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>that thou mayeſt be able to ſtand againſt the aſſaults of the Diuell. For thou wraſtleſt not againſt fleſh and bloud, but againſt principalities, againſt powers, and againſt the worldly gouernours, the Princes of the darkneſſe of this world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes, which are in high places.</hi> For this cauſe take vnto thée the whole armour of GOD, that thou mayeſt be able to reſiſt in the euill day, and hauing finiſhed all things, ſtand faſt, Stand therefore and thy loines girded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with verity, &amp; hauing on the breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate of righteouſneſſe, and thy féete ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace. Aboue all things take the ſhield of faith, wherewith thou mayeſt quench all the fierie darts of the wicked, and take the helmet of ſaluation, and the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God. In this armour come forth to the ſingle fight, and thou ſhalt returne moſt ſurely conquerour; Chriſt hath fought and ouercome for thée, he will fight and ouercome in thée, he will put vpon thée the crowne of glory.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXI.</hi> The Apoſtacie of many.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>BVt how many Souldiers of Chriſt could I reckon, which being circumuented by the craft of the Diuell, haue returned out of this battell not Conquerours, but conquered? How many could I number which haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun wel, but afterwards haue falne again from the grace of God, and the reward of eternall
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150476:45"/> life? I feare therefore the hidden counſels of God; and conſidering his ſecret iudgements, I doe wholly tremble in ſoule and boby.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>TRuly thou doeſt well,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> that thou work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt out thy ſaluation with feare and trembling, in acknowledging the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of thy fleſh, and the power of Satan that layes waite for thée, as alſo by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding narrowly the examples of thoſe, which ſliding into ſinnes, haue fallen from ſaluation; yet take héede, that thou doe not ſo obſerue thine owne infirmitie and other mens falles, and backe-ſliding, that thou doe not with-all haue reſpect to Gods mercy and power to hold thée vp, and make thée to ſtand: I will ſhew thée therefore what thou ſhalt doe. Be thou ſure in the ſpirit of the gift of perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the reward of eternall life, that notwithſtanding thou become not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by carnally ſecure. The infallible promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God doe frée thée from doubting: the exhortations and comminations of God doe free thée from carnall ſecuritie. There is ſecuritie no where in this life, but in the hope of the promiſes of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in Pſal <hi>94.</hi> Id. <hi>2.</hi> de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no perſeuer. c. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note> In this life which wholy is a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation vpon earth, he that ſéemes to ſtand, let him take héede, leaſt he fall: therefore thoſe that will not perſeuere, are mingled by the moſt prouident counſell of God with thoſe which ſhall perſeuere, that we may learne to be not loftily wiſe, but agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the humble, and worke out our
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150476:46"/> ſaluation with feare &amp; trembling. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with one eye of thine heart behold the mercie of God, but with the other the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God: out of the faithfull beholding of the mercy of God, let there ariſe in thine heart the confidence of perſeuerance; out of the feare of the iuſtice of God, let there ariſe in it the flight of carnall ſecurity. Let the feare of God wound thy fleſh, leaſt the loue of ſinfull fleſh deceiue thée.<note place="margin">Pſa. 147.11</note> 
                     <hi>The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of the Lord is in them that feare him, and hope in his mercy.</hi> Let the inward man hope and truſt, let the outward man feare and tremble.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXII.</hi> The doubting of the writing in the Booke of life.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>THey alone doe perſeuere and receiue the Crowne of perſeuerance, which are written in the Booke of life. But how may I know that I am written in that Booke?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 13.8 cap. 21.27.</note>THat Booke of life is Chriſt, from whence it is called the Booke of life of the Lambe. The writing into this Booke of life is nothing elſe but the election of the beléeuers in Chriſt to eternal life.<note place="margin">Eph. 1.5. Apoc. 17.8</note> For euen as the faithfull are ſaid to be choſen in Chriſt before the foundations of the world were laid, ſo their names are ſaid to be written in the booke of life, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world. Therefore we muſt iudge as of election, ſo alſo of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into the Booke of life, not from that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150476:46"/> which goeth before, but from that which followeth after.<note place="margin">Bern. <hi>Serm.</hi> 1. <hi>Septuag.</hi>
                     </note> There are manifeſt ſignes and tokens of ſaluation giuen, ſo that it is without all doubt that he is of the number of the choſen in whom thoſe ſignes ſhall remaine. For as many as are elected from eternity to life, they doe heare the word of ſaluation in time, they beléeue on Chriſt, they ſhew forth the fruits of the ſpirit, they perſeuere in faith.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.10</note> He therefore which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeues on the Son, hath the teſtimonie of God in himſelfe, for the holy Ghoſt doth teſtifie in the heart of beléeuers, that they are the Sons of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> and written into the Booke of life. Thoſe whom God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated from eternitie,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.20 Rom. 8.29</note> &amp; whoſe names he hath written in heauen, thoſe doth he call in time by the word, &amp; iuſtifie by true faith on Chriſt; that faith ſhewes it ſelfe forth by true inuocation of God, by pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the Croſſe, by the ſtudy of holines. Therfore let the holy &amp; wholſome medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of election and the Booke of life, begin from the wounds of Chriſt hanging on the Croſſe, hée that beléeues on him, and perſeueres in faith, is iuſtified and written into the Booke of the liuing.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.9</note> Haſt thou not béene receiued by Baptiſme into the couenant of grace, waſhed with the blood of Chriſt from thy ſinnes, regenerated and renued by the holy Ghoſt? This is an euident ſigne, that thou art written into the booke of life.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.26.27.</note> For we are all the Sons of God by faith, ſéeing as many as are baptiſed haue put on Chriſt. How com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it to paſſe that falling into ſinne,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150476:47"/> out of infirmitie after Baptiſme thou haſt not béene bruiſed?<note place="margin">Sauanar. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 31.</note> who hath put vnder his hand? who hath receiued thée againe into grace? who but the Lord? This is a great ſigne of thine election, the elect when he ſhall fall ſhall not be bruiſed. God hath written not the Tables of the deſtinies, or the decrees of <hi>Rhadamantus,</hi> but the Booke of life, when he choſe vs in Chriſt before the foundations of the world were laide. Therefore ſéeke in Chriſt, by faith, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of thée to life, and writing of thée into the Booke of life: walke by faith, that thou mayeſt come to predeſtination.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ex</hi> Aug. <hi>Lom.</hi> 6.1. <hi>ſent. diſt.</hi> 41. D.</note> They which raſhly, and without the limits of the word doe ſearch the depth of God, are plunged at length ouer head and eares in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the déepe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIII.</hi> The feare of Death.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>IT is good for mee to cleane vnto Chriſt, I will not let him depart out of my heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee bleſſe mee. I haue decreed with true faith to perſeuere in Chriſt, that it may be my lot to raigne together with him. In the meane time I confeſſe that I am not yet free from all terrour of death, neither doe I feele ſo great ſtrength and helpe of the Spirit, that with the Apoſtle I deſire ardently to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>INdéede this is the infirmitie of our fleſh, and propertie of our corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150476:47"/> that we are more deſirous of this life fading, then of the life to come that is not flitting: Hence comes that feare and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of death, which that thou mayeſt ouercome by the power of the ſpirit, and mayeſt grow in the ſtrength of the inner man, waigh thoſe things diligently, which I ſhall propoſe vnto thée out of the ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of the heauenly truth. Firſt,<note place="margin">Math. 10.30. Iob. 14.5.</note> it is certaine that euen the haires of our heads are vnder an account with God, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our moneths is appointed of him, he hath ſet vs downe a bound, which wée can by no meanes paſſe, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our dayes were written in his Booke,<note place="margin">Pſa. 139.5.</note> before any one of them was. Therefore good reaſon thou ſhouldeſt reſt thy ſelfe in this fatherly will of God; of his grace he gaue thée life, hée brought thée forth wonderfully out of the cloſe places of thy Mothers belly, as long as he would haue thée to be in life, he hath kept thée ſafe and ſound from a thouſand dangers; hée doth now aſke againe the ſoule, which heretofore he hath giuen thée, ſurely he doth not take away that which is thine, but he aſkes againe that which is his owne; now what action can there lie againſt him, which aſkes for that againe which he hath lent? Furthermore, the ſoule which hée doth require of thée, hée doth tranſlate into the ioyes of the heauenly Paradiſe, and wil reſtore the ſame againe to the body in the time to come, adorned with greater glory; and with more ſhining gifts. That body which is repoſed into the Chamber of the graue, ſhall in time
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150476:48"/> to come be a farre more glorious, worthy, and precious habitation for thy ſoule.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.42. Verſ. 43. Verſ. 44.</note> It is ſowen in corruption, it riſeth againe in incorruption. It is ſowen in diſhonour, it ſhall riſe againe in glory. It is ſowen in weakneſſe, it ſhall riſe againe in power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is ſowen a naturall body, &amp; it ſhall riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> againe a ſpirituall body. Therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend humbly and readily thy ſoule created of God, redéemed of his Son, and made the habitation of the holy Ghoſt, into the faithfull hands of God, as it were a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pledge, ſaying with <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> nay, rather with Chriſt thy head: <hi>Into thy hands I commend my ſpirit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 31.6. Act. 7.59. Luk. 23.46</note> 
                     <hi>thou haſt redeemed mee, O God of truth.</hi> Note this alſo that in the very agonie of death thou mayeſt moſt ſurely promiſe to thy ſelfe the preſence and helpe of God; for ſéeing thou doeſt embrace Chriſt thy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour with a true faith, being moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely perſwaded, that with his death he hath ouercome thine, and hath reſtored vnto thée righteouſneſſe and immortall life by his reſurrection,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> therefore iuſtified by this faith, thou haſt peace with God, and thou mayeſt be raiſed vp in the midſt of death by the helpe of thy heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Iob. 13.15. Pſa. 91.15.</note> that thou mayeſt ſay with <hi>Iob: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Lord ſhall kill me, yet will I truſt in him. I am with him in trouble,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will deliuer him, and I will glorifie him; with length of dayes will I fill him, and ſhew him my ſaluation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.39</note> 
                     <hi>From this loue of God, neither life, nor death, neither any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall be able to ſeparate or to pull thee</hi>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:150476:48"/> away, ſéeing it is in Ieſus Chriſt, which is a king eternall, and our Sauiour for euer. The accuſation of the law makes the ſhape of death terrible, that I ſay, and the deformitie of ſinne,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55.</note> and the tentation of being euerlaſtingly caſt away, ſéeing the ſting of death is ſinne, the ſtrength of ſinne is the law: but call to thy memory the conſolation which is before oppoſed to theſe monſters, and all that outward hope of death, terrible to be beheld, will vaniſh, and will be changed into a moſt pleaſant ſléepe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIIII.</hi> The ſting of Death.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>BY ſinne death hath entred into the world, and is the due wages of ſinne, how there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould I not be ſore afraid of death?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>TRuly, death in it ſelfe, and by it ſelfe, is the wages of ſinne, and the reuenging ſcourge of the angry God, but to thoſe that beléeue in Chriſt it is changed into a moſt ſwéet ſléepe. For although the regenerate and thoſe that beléeue in Chriſt, doe as yet carry about the reliques of ſinne in their fleſh, from whence alſo their body is dead,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.10</note> that is to ſay, ſubiect to death for the ſinne that dwels in it, yet the ſpirit is life for righteouſneſſe, that is, becauſe they are iuſtified from ſins by true ſaith in Chriſt, and reſiſt the luſts of the fleſh through the ſpirit, therefore that ſinne which yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150476:49"/> in the fleſh is not imputed vnto them,<note place="margin">Gregor. Nyſſen. in orat. de mort.</note> but is couered with the ſhadow of the grace of God: therefore by death the true and ſpiritual life of the ſoule doth not dye in them, but doth rather beginne, to which death is conſtrained, as it were, to doe the office of a Midwife. Thence flow thoſe moſt ſwéet appellations by which the holy Ghoſt, which is the ſpirit of truth, doth deſcribe the death of the godly: for they which before the eyes of fooles doe ſéeme, and of them are ſayd to dye, the holy Ghoſt ſayth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen. 25.8. Cap. 35.29. Cap. 49.33</hi> Tertull. lib. de patient. p. <hi>12.</hi> Cyprian. de mortal. p. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>4.</hi> Chry. hom. <hi>45.</hi> in Gen. Col. <hi>375.</hi> Hilar in Pſal. <hi>140.</hi> Ambr. de boum. ort. cap. <hi>10. 2 Pet. 1.15</hi>
                     </note> that they are gathered or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated to their people, that is, to the company of the bleſſed and triumphing Church in Heauen, to come to thoſe which haue deceaſed before them in the true faith, or rather haue gone before them. It is but the taking of a iourney, which we thinke to be death, it is not an end, but a paſſage; it is not ſo much an emigration, as a tranſmigration from worſe things to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a taking away of the ſoule, and a moſt bleſſed carrying of it from place to place, not an aboliſhing, for the ſoule is taken away and tranſpoſed into a place of reſt, it is not kild vp. It is a paſſage and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion to the true life. It is an outgoing, becauſe by it the godly paſſe out of the ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of ſinne to true libertie, euen as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore the Iſraelites out of the bondage of Egypt into the promiſed Land.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 5 24. Eſa. 57.2.</note>The godly are ſaid by death to come to peace, and to reſt in their chambers, that is, becauſe they come out of that daily warfare vpon earth to a place of peace:
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150476:49"/> out of the moſt troubleſome ſea of this life to the hauen: out of the moſt laborious priſon of this life to a place of reſt:<note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> they are ſaid to be looſed &amp; to come to Chriſt: ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are led out of the Inne of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, to the heauenly Countrie, and out of the dregs of wicked men, to the moſt bleſſed ſocietie of Chriſt in Heauen: they are looſed by death out of the bands of the body: for euen as the Cattell when they haue diſcharged the labours of the whole day, at laſt about the euening are ſet frée, and euen as they which are bound in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, are looſed of their fetters: ſo the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are ledde forth by death from the ſayd yoake of the labours and ſorrowes of this life, and out of the filthy priſon of ſinne,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.5. 2 Cor. 5.8.</note> and by a moſt ſwéet tranſlation are carried to a better life. They are ſayd to go forth of the land of their pilgrimage by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the tabernacle of their body, and to be preſent with the Lord, and that becauſe they come out of the ruinous ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of the world to the heauenly pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, out of an houſe of clay to a citty made without hands, eternall in the heauens, out of the tabernacle of an earthly body, to the heauenly Ieruſalem, and the moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſociety of Chriſt abiding therein.</p>
                  <p>It is his property therefore to feare death, which would not goe to Chriſt:<note place="margin">Cypr. ſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. demortal. pa. <hi>208.</hi>
                     </note> It is his property not to be willing to goe to Chriſt, which doth not beléeue to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to raigne with Chriſt. They are ſayd to reſt from their labours, for not the man, but the miſery of a godly man dieth.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150476:50"/> If this life be full of burden,<note place="margin">Caeciliae vox. Ambroſ. de bono mortis. cap. <hi>2. 1 Cor. 15.38.</hi>
                     </note> then the end is the eaſe therof: but death is a good eaſe, but death is an end, death therfore is good. They are ſayd to be ſowed into the earth, or field of the Lord by death and buriall, ſéeing the bodies of the godly, as it were, precious graines of Wheat ſhall againe bud forth hereafter to life.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Stigeliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>This Corneth immortall glory of the fleſh,</l>
                     <l>Doth ſhew from liueles body ſpringing freſh,</l>
                     <l>Vnder the clods is caſt the ſapleſſe ſeed,</l>
                     <l>Of which a man would thinke could nothing breed:</l>
                     <l>Yet this doth riſe by hidden motion growing,</l>
                     <l>Increas'd in ſtrength and body from the ſowing:</l>
                     <l>Likewiſe our bodyes layd in hollow graue,</l>
                     <l>Thence riſing, laſting life and glory haue,</l>
                     <l>Firſt drown'd in death, now lifes true badge they weare,</l>
                     <l>And before God eternall bliſſe doe ſhare.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The bones of the godly ſhall bud forth and flouriſh in the time to come,<note place="margin">Eſa. 66.14. 2 Reg. 7.12 Eſa. 26.20. Dan. 12.2. Matt. 9.24. Ioh. 11.11 1 Cor. 15.6. 1 Theſſal. 4.13.</note> when the ſpring of the life eternall ſhall beginne: finally, they are ſaid to ſlumber and to ſléep a certaine ſwéet ſléep, for euen as in ſléepe we reſt from labour, wee gather our deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſtrength, the ſoule in the meane time exerciſing her operations: ſo by death being lead to reſt from all the labours and ſorrowes of this life, wee gather new ſtrength of minde and body, to execute thoſe workes more readily and perfectly, to which we were in the beginning created
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150476:50"/> and redéemed by Chriſt, the ſoule in the meane time liuing and reioycing in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Euen as in ſléepe wee doe not care what is done about vs, neither are wee troubled with the troubles of humane bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes: ſo they that are godlily dead in the Lord doe reſt from all care and trouble, neither are they further ſubiect to the euils of this life. Euen as we are againe raiſed vp out of ſléepe, ſo death ſhall not be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſleepe, but the houre will come, in which wee ſhall heare the voyce of Chriſt calling vs out of the graue, and wee ſhall come forth againe to life.<note place="margin">Auguſt. ſer. <hi>44.</hi> de ver. Dom.</note> No man doth ſo eaſily raiſe vp one that lyes vpon his bed, as Chriſt the dead out of his graue. Out of al which it clearely appeareth how truely the Apoſtle hath called the death of the godly aduantage,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> ſéeing it is aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to haue eſcaped the increaſe of ſinne: it is aduantage to haue auoyded worſe things: it is aduantage to paſſe to better. The death of the godly is precious in the ſight of the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſa. 116.15.</note> and to them it is good for reſt, better for ſecuritie, beſt of all for bleſſedneſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXV.</hi> The ſorrowes of Death.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Feare not death but the ſorrowes of death; for I haue often ſeene the eyes of dying men waxing dimme, their eares waxing deafe, their tongue waxing ſtiffe: I haue ſeene the ſweat and anxitie, the horror and nakedneſſe of men that dye: I haue oftentimes heard the how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150476:51"/> and complaint of the ſoule, compelled to goe forth of the houſe of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>THoſe that beléeue in Chriſt are kept from thoſe ſorrowes of death, or ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſorrowes are mittigated vnto them. Chriſt hath taken vpon himſelfe that which was moſt bitter in our death, that is to ſay, the ſenſe and féeling of the wrath of God:<note place="margin">Exod. 15.25. Iohn 5 51.</note> let vs caſt the wood of the Croſſe, on which Chriſt dyed for vs, into our death, and behold, it will be vnto vs a pleaſant ſléepe. <hi>Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>if any man keepe my word hee ſhall not ſee death for euer:</hi> that is to ſay, he ſhall not onely not ſée eternal death, but alſo neither that cruell and horrible ſhape of temporall death. And if ſo bee ſome ſmall taſte of bitterneſſe be offered vnto vs out of the cup of death, what and how little is that in reſpect of that brooke, of which Chriſt dranke for vs in the way of this life?<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.7.</note> how little is that ſmal draught to be eſtéemed in reſpect of that cup, which the heauenly Father hath offered vnto Chriſt to be drunke vp wholy in our ſtéed?<note place="margin">Mat. 26.42.</note> Our death is as it were a certaine medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable purgation of the ſoule &amp; of the body,<note place="margin">The ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodius.</hi>
                     </note> ſéeing by it the poyſon of ſin is as it were, purged out of our fleſh, what maruell is it, if ſome Aloes be mixt with this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation? Our death is the midwife to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, what maruaile is it if the ſame happen vnto vs, which happens to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant borne into the world out of the narrow
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150476:51"/> places of his Mothers wombe, which muſt in part beare the ſorrowes of trauel. There is no birth without all griefe: that ſharpe fit will endure but a ſhort moment, and behold the day of our deeth will be the birth-day of eternall life. Narrow is that gate which leades vs to life, what maruell is it if we féele ſome trouble in the going out thereof?<note place="margin">Mich. 2.13</note> Chriſt is our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and hée that hath broken vp the way for vs, he layes open the iourney be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, we muſt cleaue vnto him by true faith, that we may paſſe through the gate of death together with him, and finde the way to eternall life, knowne vnto him. Sinne doth as yet dwell in our fleſh,<note place="margin">Pſa. 16.11</note> what maruell is it, if for the remainder of ſinne wée are conſtrained to ſuffer ſome ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of death?<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1. Eph. 2.14.</note> In the meane time our conſcience hath peace in Chriſt, which is our true peace, which riſing againe from the dead, hath brought to vs the gift of peace. There remaines no dart to Death, by which it may wound our ſoule, it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens his téeth in our héele, but the poiſon is taken away from it of Chriſt, that it cannot powre it into vs, together with the téeth that it hath faſtned.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVI.</hi> Too timely Death.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>ME thinkes I am called backe too timely out of this life,<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.25. Pſa. 58.23.</note> God ſnatcheth mee away in the midſt of my dayes, I feare therefore leaſt this be a ſigne of the wrath of God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150476:52"/> it is written: men of bloud and deceipt ſhall not liue out halfe their dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>NOthing is too timely with GOD, which is ripe. Long life truly is the gift of God, yet ſhort life is not alwayes a token of the wrath of GOD, ſéeing GOD ſometimes alſo commands the godly, and thoſe that are beloued of him to depart timely out of the houſe of this world, that being fréed from the danger of ſinning, they may be ſet into the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of not ſinning, neither be conſtrained to haue experience of publike calamities oft-times more grieuous then death it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Eſa. 26.20.</note> The people of GOD goeth, and enter into their Chambers, they ſhall ſhut the dores vpon them, they are hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for a moment, till the indignation paſſe away.<note place="margin">Eſa. 57.1.</note> 
                     <hi>The iuſt man periſheth, and there is no man that conſidereth in his heart: the mercifull men are taken away, and there is none which doth vnderſtand.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>The iuſt man is taken away from the face of euill: peace ſhall come vnto him, hee that walkes vprightly,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sap 4.7.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall reſt in his Chamber. The iuſt man although hee be preuented by death, ſhall be in refreſhing:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>For reuerend olde age ſtands not in the length of dayes, neyther is it reckoned in the number of yeeres.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>The vnderſtanding of a man is his gray haires, and olde age is the vndefiled life.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> Hee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed GOD, and vvas beloued, and liuing amongſt ſinners, hee vvas tranſlated. Hee
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150476:52"/> was taken away leaſt vvickedneſſe ſhould change his vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> and leaſt fayning ſhould deceiue his ſoule.<note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> For vvickedneſſe by bewitching obſcureth the things that are good, and the vnſtedfaſtneſſe of concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence peruerteth the ſimple minde.<note place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note> Though hee was ſoone dead, yet fulfilled hee much time, for his ſoule pleaſed GOD,<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haſted hee to take him away from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>The drye vnhappie Tree vvhich yeelds no fruit,</l>
                     <l>Is hewen downe, and falling doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne</l>
                     <l>Her barren boughes, they ſpare the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Tree:</l>
                     <l>The Law of Heauen's contrarie.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Therefore the godly man dies well, whether he die in a good age, or in the firſt flower of his youth.<note place="margin">Sph. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſ c.</hi> 36. <hi>p.</hi> 411.</note> What other thing is our life, but ſtrife? What is our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe, but a graue? What is our bodie, but bonds? What is our generation, but a thruſting forth into the earth? Wilt thou take it in euill part that thou art timely fréed from theſe euils and bonds? By how much the more timely the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Generall doth call thée backe out of the ſtation of this life, by ſo much the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth he place thée into a place of reſt, peace and victory.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:150476:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVII.</hi> Seruices farther due to the Church.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Might in my place by mine endeauour, ſuch as it is for the time to come further profit the Church of God, for this end therefore I could wiſh, that the ſpace of a longer life might be granted vnto me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>ALL this muſt be commended to Gods diſpoſing, that is, how long God will haue thée to remaine in health and life for the Miniſterie of his Church.<note place="margin">The words of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> at his death, as mentions <hi>Poſidon,</hi> in the life of <hi>Auguſt. C.</hi> 27. Phil. 1.23.</note> Say there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with that old Doctor of the Church, and well-deſeruing Biſhop. I haue not ſo liued that I am aſhamed to liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, neither yet doe I feare to die becauſe wée haue a good Lord. Hée that hath furniſhed thée with the gifts of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching for the profit of his Church, knowes alſo to furniſh others with the ſame. Therefore if thou art ſtraightned with the Apoſtle, that thou knoweſt not which of theſe two thou ſhouldeſt chuſe: hauing a deſire to be diſſolued and to be with Chriſt, which is better for thée, or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in the fleſh, which is more profitable for the Church; know that to die is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage to thée, but to liue is profit to the Church.<note place="margin">Rom. 14.7</note> 
                     <hi>No man of vs liueth to himſelfe, and no man dieth to himſelfe.</hi> For whether we liue, we liue to the Lord, (to the end that we may gaine more ſoules to him in the Church) or whether we dye, we dye
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150476:53"/> to the Lord (that we may obey his father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will, calling vs out of our ſtation) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therefore we liue, or whether we dye, we are the Lords (that moſt gentle and mightie Lord,<note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> from whoſe loue neither life nor death can ſeparate vs. Thou haſt hitherto obeyed the will of the Lord, moſt faithfully ſpending thy ſeruices on the Church; obey him further, moſt readily embracing his will that calls thée to the ſocietie of the Church triumphant. Thou art rightly carefull out of charitie for the encreaſe of the Church, notwithſtanding thou oughteſt out of faith to commit the care of gouerning and conſeruing the Church to God. There is nothing here more wholſome, nothing better, nothing more conformable to pietie then for a man to reſigne himſelfe wholly to the will of God, and to commend the full power of diſpoſing of our life &amp; death to him with godly prayers.<note place="margin">Bern. <hi>in meditat de votiſſ. c.</hi> 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 1196. Pſa. 37.5.</note> One of theſe two things we may vndoubtedly hope for, either hée will giue vs that which we aſke, or that which he knoweth to be more profitable. Commend thy way to the Lord, and hope in him, and he will doe it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVIII.</hi> Shortneſſe of life drawne on by our owne accord, or our life abridged by our owne default.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Feare leaſt that I haue made my life ſhorter by my ſinnes, how then can I hope for the preſence and helpe of God in death? they
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150476:54"/> that are guiltie of their owne death, ſhall not finde a better life after death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>AYe, but that is to be vnderſtoode of them which out of impatience lay vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent hands vpon themſelues, and compell their ſoule to goe out of the houſe of their body againſt the will of GOD, farre be ſuch a purpoſe from thy pietie;<note place="margin">Auguſt. 1. <hi>de ciu. Dei.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.26.</note> for it is lawfull for no man to bring vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe voluntarie death, as it were deſiring to eſcape temporall troubles, leaſt he fall into the euerlaſting; this is lawfull for no man for other mens ſinnes, leaſt he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to haue this moſt heauie ſinne his owne, whom other mens ſinnes did not pollute: this is lawfull for no man for ſinnes paſt, for which he hath more néede of this life, that by repentance they may be healed: this is lawfull for no man for the deſire of a better life, which is expected after death, becauſe they that are guiltie of their owne death, ſhall not finde a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life after death. But if thy minde be troubled with thoſe thoughts, that thou haſt made thy life ſhorter by immoderate vſe of meate or drinke, or by any other diſorder, bewaile this with earneſt ſighes, and place all thy truſt on Chriſtes me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, conceiuing firmely a purpoſe of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life, and GOD will be mercifull to thine iniquities, which hath promiſed pardon of all their offences to them that truly repent. <hi>Manaſſes</hi> a man of bloud had broken off the thread of his life, yet ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150476:54"/> repenting he hath obtained the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the eternall life.<note place="margin">Luk. 23.41</note> The Thiefe on the Croſſe had receiued things worthie of his doing, yet being earneſtly conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto God, hée entred into Paradiſe with Chriſt.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> And had not our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents drawne death vpon themſelues and all their poſteritie, neuertheleſſe embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing that Euangelicall promiſe of the bruiſer of the Serpents head, they were lifted vp againe by quickning conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">The word of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> the Emperour.</note> Wherefore if thou haſt followed theſe in their ſinnes, follow them alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting with teares. The hand of God is not yet ſhortned, neither hath his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie failed in the number of yéeres: the gate of indulgence is not yet ſhalte, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is yet graunted a time of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIX.</hi> The loue of this life.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Could wiſh that I might yet enioy a more laſting vſe of this life, and the profits thereof. I could wiſh that I might poſſeſſe yet longer the bleſſings of God granted vnto me in this life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>TAke héede that thou doe not make it manifeſt by the inordinate loue of this life, that thou doeſt not truly loue the chiefeſt good.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſelm.</hi> de menſura crucis lit. E.</note> So doe we owe our whole heart to the loue of God, that whatſoeuer is giuen thereof to another, is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150476:55"/> from God. Hée loues God the leſſe which loues any thing with him, which he loues not for him. Thy heart is a veſſell, but it is full of the loue of the world, therefore there is no place for the true loue of God to enter: powre out the loue of the world, that the loue of God may enter. What doth this preſent life ſo much delight thée, which is wholly a dangerous and hard warfare? What o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing is it to liue long, then long to be tormented,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cypria.</hi> Serm. de mortal. pag. <hi>215.</hi>
                     </note> and long to ſinne? If in the houſe of thy dwelling, the walles ſhould ſhake for age, the roofe aboue thée tremble, the houſe being now wearied, and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnder the buildings that ſlide downe with age, ſhould threaten a ruine néere at hand, wouldeſt thou not goe forth with all haſt? If while thou wert ſayling, a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome and ſtormie tempeſt, the waues being raiſed vp by the force of the winde, ſhould fore-ſhew ſhipwracke to come, wouldeſt thou not make toward the hauen with all haſt? Behold, the world ſhakes and ſlides away, and teſtifies the ruine of it ſelfe, not now by the olde age, but by the end of things, and doeſt not thou giue God thankes, doeſt thou not reioyce on thine owne behalfe, that being taken away with a more timely end, thou art ſaued from ruines, ſhipwrackes, and imminent plagues?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> in ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>8.</hi> ad Rom.</note> Euen as the Sea ſtirred vp by contrarie ſtormes doth riſe, and maketh a tempeſt to thoſe that ſaile: ſo the world being ſtirred by the conſpiracie of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous, doth trouble the mindes of the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150476:55"/> faithfull, and the enemie deales ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſely, that wée are ignorant what wée ſhould firſt ſhunne. For if power doth ceaſe to be againſt vs, he ſtirres the mindes of priuate men; If theſe be appeaſed, hée blowes vp a combuſtion by thoſe of our owne houſe. And if this alſo be allayed, by his cunning he makes diſcord betwéene brethren themſelues, ſo that the houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhaken at the foure corners, one ſome part begins to fall: wherefore with one conſent Chriſtians muſt flye hence. For they ought to follow the example of the holy man,<note place="margin">Simeon.</note> which knowing that they doe here wage warre againſt treacherie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that hée might be let to depart in peace. Surely this life appeares to be a pretious Nut outwardly, but if it be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the knife of truth, there will be found nothing in it, but vanitie and emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe. If there be any good in this life, that is eminently, nay incomparably bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in that other. That is in faith, this in fight; that in the time of peregrination, this in the eternity of manſion: that is in labour, this is in reſt: that is in the way, this in the Countrey:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſt.</hi> trac. vlt. in <hi>Ioh.</hi>
                     </note> that is in the worke of action, this in the reward of contemplation: that declines from euill, and doth good, this hath none euill from which it may decline, &amp; it hath great good, which it may enioy: that fights with the enemie, this raignes without an enemie: that is valiant in aduerſity, this feeles no aduerſitie: that bridles carnall luſts, this ſpends the time in ſpirituall delights:
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150476:56"/> that is troubled with the care of ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming, this is ſecure in the peace of victorie: that is helped in tentations, this without any tentation reioyceth in the helper himſelfe: that helpes the néedie, this is there where it findes none néedie: that forgiues other mens ſinnes, that her owne may be pardoned vnto her, this neither ſuffers that which ſhée may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, nor doth that which ſhe may require to be forgiuen vnto her: That is ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with euils, leaſt it ſhould be lifted vp with proſperitie, this in ſo great fulneſſe of grace wants all euill, that without any tentation of pride it may cleaue to the chiefeſt good: That diſcernes good and euill, this ſées thoſe things which are onely good. Chuſe therefore which is to be preferd before other. Lay aſide the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate deſire of the fading life, leaſt thou léeſe the inheritance of the abiding. So hold thoſe things which are of this world, that notwithſtanding thou be not held by them: Let the earthly ſubſtance be poſſeſt of thée, but let it not poſſeſſe thée: Let that which thou haſt be vnder the dominion of thy minde, leaſt thy minde, while it is ouercome with the loue of earthly, be it ſelfe more poſſeſſed of the things themſelues.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cypria.</hi> Serm. de morta.</note> Why doeſt thou not make haſt to better things? Now hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things ſuccéede earthly, and great things the ſmall, and eternall things the periſhing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:150476:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XL.</hi> The ſeparation from Wife, Children, and Kinsfolkes.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Muſt leaue my moſt ſweet children; I muſt leaue my moſt faithfull wife; I muſt leaue my moſt pleaſant kinsfolkes; who ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for my wife and children? who will be their defender and Patrone?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>IT is God which calles himſelfe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Orphanes,<note place="margin">Pſa. 68.6.</note> and the defender of widdowes, commend them to his Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and defence. God which is thy God,<note place="margin">Gen 17.</note> will alſo be the GOD of thy ſeede. Thy children are not thine onely, but they are alſo Gods, nay they are more Gods then thine, ſeeing he hath beſtowed more things vpon them, canſt thou therefore doubt of the fatherly care of God towards them? The Prophet of the Lord doth teſtifie, <hi>that he hath beene young, and alſo olde,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 37.25</note> 
                     <hi>yet neuer did he ſee the righteous forſaken, or his ſeed to begge their bread.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 112.2</note> 
                     <hi>The generation of the righteous ſhall be bleſſed at length.</hi> God hath promiſed to thy children the heauenly treaſures, hée will not ſuffer them, beléeue mée, to periſh for hunger. Hée hath giuen them life, he wil not deny them the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of life: he hath giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a body, that which he hath wonderfully framed, he wil alſo kindely ſuſtaine. But take héede, that thou be not ſo carefull for the bodily ſafety of thy wife and children, that in the meane
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150476:57"/> time thou neglect the care of thy ſoule.<note place="margin">Luk. 14.26</note> 
                     <hi>If any man come to me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and doth not hate his Father, and Mother, and Wife, and Children, and Brothers, and Siſters, yea and his owne ſoule, he cannot be my Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 10.37.</note> that he expoundeth elſe-where ſo: <hi>He that loueth Father or Mother more then mee, is not worthy of me: and he that loueth ſonne or daughter more then me, is not worthie of me.</hi> Behold God calles thée by death, take héede thou doe not ſo loue thy wife and children, that therefore thou refuſe to follow God, calling thée, with a readie heart. The loue of the heauenly Father muſt be preferred before the loue of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ambro.</hi> in cap. <hi>12.</hi> p. <hi>111. Bern.</hi> Serm. <hi>26.</hi> in Cant. Col. <hi>569. Auguſt.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>6.</hi> ad Vid.</note> the loue of our Bridegroome Chriſt muſt be ſet before the loue of wife, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit muſt not more be loued then the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactour. What ſhall I ſpeake of kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? if thou leaueſt thoſe that are deare, thou ſhalt receiue them héereafter more déere. For wée doe hope on a moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promiſe, that when we goe out of this life, whence being to depart, we haue not loſt, but ſent before, ſome of ours, that are departed: we ſhall come to that life, where by how much they ſhall be better knowne of vs, ſo much they ſhall be dearer vnto vs, and without the feare of any diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, amiable. If thy kinſmen be déere vnto thée, let Chriſt be déerer, which is thy brother. If it be a pleaſant thing to be here conuerſant with thy kinſmen,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.22</note> let it be more pleaſant vnto thee, that thou commeſt to the mount Sion,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er. 23.</note> and Citie of the liuing God the heauenly Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150476:57"/> and to the company of innumerable Angels, and to the congregation of the firſt borne, which are written in heauen, and to God, the iudge of all, and to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of iuſt and perfect men.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLI.</hi> The ſtopping vp of the eares in Death.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Feare leſt that my eares waxing deafe in the agony of death, I ſhall be deſtituted of all conſolation of heart, and too much vexed with the terrours of Satan.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>THe inward comfort of the ſpirit is of greater force then all outward conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16</note> The holy ſpirit giues teſtimonie to our ſpirit that wee are the ſonnes of God: the ſame ſpirit doth raiſe vp our ſpirit, when wee beginne to wraſtle with death, and to be troubled in heart, for he is the true and greateſt comforter.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.26</note> When thine eyes waxe dimme in death, the holy Ghoſt will giue vnto thée the true illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the heart: when thine eares waxe deafe in death, he will giue vnto thée the quickening conſolation of the ſoule. Where mans conſolation ſhall ceaſe, there Gods conſalation will begin. Behold the examples of the Martyrs, how prompt and ready they were to the moſt exquiſite puniſhments: the whéeles ſéemed to them Roſes: the ſparkes of fire ſpirituall brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150476:58"/> the yron chaines, golden crownes, the torments, ornaments, the two edged ſwords, beames of the heauenly light: who hath wrought this in their hearts, who hath comforted them in ſorrowes but the holy Ghoſt? His conſolation is of greater force then the accuſation of the whole world; yea, of the prince of the world. What? Doeſt thou thinke that the holy Ghoſt doth onely lift vp our hearts in the courſe of this life, and doth idlely reſt in the agony of death? Doſt thou thinke that the habitation of the holy Ghoſt is deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> when the tabernacle of the body is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed?<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.2.</note> Chriſt liues in thée, and dwels by faith in thy heart, grace is powred out in his lips, in the fragrancy of this grace, hee will make glad thine heart,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45 9.</note> although thine hearing periſh: his ſpéech will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ierce to thine heart, although the dores of thine eares be ſhut.<note place="margin">Eſa. 61.1.</note> The ſpirit of the Lord is vpon him, the Lord hath annointed him to preach the Goſpell to the afflicted, hée hath ſent him to binde vp the broken in heart, to preach fréedome to the captiues, and opening of priſon to thoſe that are bound.<note place="margin">Eſa. 50 4.</note> The Lord hath giuen vnto him a learned tongue, that hee may know to comfort &amp; ſuſtaine the afflicted in a ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able time. Cleane to him with firme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of thy heart, commend thy ſelfe to him with godly prayers, hee will comfort thée in the ſeaſonable time, he will raiſe vp thine heart with the word of the Goſpell, when the arrowes of death are faſtened in it, hee will binde vp thy heart, when the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150476:58"/> wounds of death are inflicted on it, hée will preach deliuerance to thy heart, when thou art led captiue of death, as it were, a pray, he will preach opening to thy heart, when thou art thruſt into the priſon of death.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLII.</hi> The apparant in vtilitie of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>IF Chriſt hath redeemed vs from death, why muſt I as yet dye? How ſhall death be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by Chriſt, when hee ſhewes his daily prayes, as it were the trophees of his victory?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>EVen as Chriſt hath ſaued his people from their ſinnes,<note place="margin">Mat 11.21</note> not that ſinne may no more dwell in their fleſh, ſéeing in this life they remayne ſolde vnder ſinne, but that he may not condemne them for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, as being regenerate and belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: ſo alſo hee hath redéemed vs from death,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.10</note> not that we ſhould not any more be ſubiect to temporall death, ſéeing that our body is dead, or ſubiect vnto death for ſinne, but that wee might be frée from the bands of eternall death. The death of the ſoule is the true death, from this Chriſt hath redéemed vs, ſuſtaining the puniſhment for vs. Swéet Ieſus hath alſo made temporal death it ſelfe ſwéet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that it is death in name alone, but in very déed ſléep, nay the end of death, and the beginning of true life. Thoſe that are truly godly doe dye daily,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.24.</note> by reaſon of thoſe continuall calamities, by which they
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150476:59"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:150476:59"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:150476:60"/> are oppreſſed in this life, therefore their death is the end of death: but by the gate of death they paſſe to a quiet and eternall life,<note place="margin">Oſe. 13.14.</note> therefore their death is the beginning of true life.</p>
                  <p>The death of Chriſt is the poyſon of our death, although therefore this poyſon hath not altogether kild our death, for it doth as yet moue it ſelfe and faſtens his dart in our héele, yet this poyſon is gone to the heart of death, it will come to paſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.26</note> that at length, by the force thereof, it dye: death is that laſt enemie, whom Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt at length in the laſt day ſhall vtterly deſtroy,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.22</note> and comming vpon this ſtrong armed man with greater ſtrength ſhall take away powerfully from him all his pray. Death muſt be beheld with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eyes, and it will appeare that his wrath is but vaine, without ſtrength, as being captiuated and ouercome of Chriſt. It layes ſnares for the life of the godly, and behold, it brings them to the true life. It attempts to kill their ſoule and body with his darts, and behold the ſoule being trée and without hurt of all wound of death, the body alone is wounded, which ſame alſo in the time to come ſhall bee ſnatcht out of the Iawes of death. It en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours to deliuer the godly to eternall death, and behold, it deliuers them to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:150476:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXIII.</hi> The horrour of the Duſt.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>WHatſoeuer it be I ſee that I muſt be laid downe into the earth, and be brought to duſt. A bed ſhall be made for my body in the graue; therefore haue I ſayd to corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Thou art my Father, and to the wormes,<note place="margin">Iob 17.14.</note> yee are my Mother and my Siſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>DOe not regard that duſt and aſhes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which thou art to be brought, but regard that future reſurrection out of the duſt and aſhes, which we expect by faith. If thou haſt ſaid with <hi>Iob,</hi> to corruption that it is thy Father, ſay with the ſame, that thy redéemer liueth,<note place="margin">Iob 19.25</note> which in the laſt day ſhall raiſe thée vp againe out of the earth, ſhall compaſſe thée about with thy ſkinne, that in thy fleſh thou mayeſt ſée thy God. The ſayings of the Scriptures, the moments of arguments, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of thoſe that were raiſed againe, doe proue this bleſſed reſurrection of our bodies. The ſayings of the Scriptures in the olde and new Teſtament are in a readineſſe, in number many, in weight moſt great, in perſpicuitie moſt cleare.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.10 Chap. 25.8 Chap. 35.29. Chap. 49.33.</note> The bloud of <hi>Abell</hi> doth cry to the Lord, in whoſe ſight as yet he liueth. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches are gathered by death vnto their people, therfore by death they do not ceaſe to be the liuing people of the liuing God.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150476:61"/> God is the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iaacob:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 3.6.</note> now God is not the God of the dead, but of the liuing: therefore <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 22.31</note> and <hi>Iaacob,</hi> doe liue before God: they liue, I ſay, in their better part, and their bodies in the time to come ſhall be called backe againe to life: nay, they are already called backe,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.53</note> ſéeing that Chriſt being riſen againe, they are riſen againe with him. <hi>I know</hi> (ſayth <hi>Iob) that my redeemer liueth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 19.25.</note> 
                     <hi>and in the laſt day I ſhall be raiſed vp againe out of the earth.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſa. 26 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Thy dead ſhall liue</hi> (ſayth <hi>Eſayas) my ſlaine ſhall riſe againe. Awake and ſing,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſa. 66.14.</note> 
                     <hi>yee that dwell in the duſt, for thy dew is as the dewe of greene hearbs: your bones ſhall flouriſh like an hearbe.</hi> For this ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">Ezek. 37.5.</note> of the dry bones: <hi>Behold, I will ſend my ſpirit into you, and ye ſhall liue, and I will lay ſinewes vpon you, and make fleſh growe vpon you, and couer you with skinne, and put breath into you, that ye may liue, and yee ſhall know that I am the Lord.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 12.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Many</hi> (ſayth <hi>Daniel) of thoſe which ſleep in the duſt of the earth ſhall awake, ſome to life eternall, others to euerlaſting ſhame. The greateſt King of the world</hi> (ſay the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Martyrs in the <hi>Maccabees) will raiſe vs when we are dead,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Mac. 7.9.</note> 
                     <hi>to eternall life, of God doe we hope that wee ſhall receiue our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.28.</note> 
                     <hi>The houre commeth</hi> (ſaith the Truth) <hi>in which all that are in the graues ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">verſ. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſhall come forth, they that haue done good to the reſurrection of life, but they that haue done euill to the reſurrection of iudgement. This is the will of the Father which hath ſent me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh 6.39.</note>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:150476:61"/> 
                     <hi>that of all which he hath giuen me, I ſhould loſe nothing, but ſhould raiſe it vp againe at the laſt day.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. 40.44</note> 
                     <hi>But this is the will of my Father which hath ſent mee, that euery one which ſeeth the Son, and beleeueth on him, haue life eternal,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. 54.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; I wil raiſe him vp again in the laſt day. I am the reſurrection and the life, he that beleeueth on me, although he were dead,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 11. verſ. 25. verſ. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>yet ſhal he liue, and euery one that liueth and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth on me ſhall not dye for euer. I haue hope on God,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) and I looke for the reſurrection to come of the iuſt &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 24.15</note> 
                     <hi>This corruptible muſt put on incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; this mortal muſt put on immortality,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.53.</note> then ſhall be fulfilled the word which is written, <hi>Death is ſwallowed vp into victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.14</note> 
                     <hi>Wee know that hee that hath raiſed vp our Lord Ieſus, hee alſo by Ieſus will raiſe vs vp. Our conuerſation is in Heauen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 3 20.</note> 
                     <hi>from whence alſo wee looke for our Sauiour the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>which ſhall change our vile body that it may be like his glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, according to the working whereby hee is able to ſubdue all things to himſelfe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.14.</note> 
                     <hi>If we beleeue that Ieſus is dead, and riſen againe, euen ſo them which ſleepe in Ieſus will God bring with him. Iohn</hi> ſaw the dead, great and ſmall, ſtanding in the ſight of God, and the bookes were opened:<note place="margin">Apoc. 20.12.</note> 
                     <hi>and the Sea gaue vp the dead which were in her, and death and hell gaue vp then dead.</hi> To theſe ſayings of Scripture written as it were, with a beame of the Sunne, may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnmoueable props of reaſons: for ſo the Apoſtle concludes,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.12.</note> 
                     <hi>If Chriſt bee riſen againe, we alſo ſhall riſe againe,</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150476:62"/> the reſurrection of Chriſt to be the key of our ſepulchres, and the example of our hope.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertul. de carne. p.</hi> 33. 1 Cor. 15.20 Exod. 23.19. Leuit. 23.20. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 20. <hi>de Trinit. cap.</hi> 17. Epheſ. 2.6.</note> CHRIST is become the firſt fruits of thoſe that ſleepe, ſayth the Apoſtle. As therefore the harueſt, by the ordinance of God, did follow the oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the firſt fruits: ſo the harueſt of the vniuerſall reſurrection ſhall follow the firſt fruits of the Lords reſurrection. Chriſt is our head, that which hath gone before in the head, ſhall follow in the members, and hence the Apoſtle doth confidently pronounce, that <hi>we are raiſed together with Chriſt, and placed in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the heauenly Paradiſe.</hi> For there is in the man Chriſt the fleſh of euery one of vs,<note place="margin">Maximi. in ſerm. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrect.</note> the bloud and portion. Where therefore our portion raignes, there doe we beléeue to raigne, where our bloud beares rule, wee féele our ſelues to beare rule, and where our fleſh is in glory, wee know that we are glorious.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.21.</note> Beſides, as by one man, that is to ſay, the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> came death: ſo by one man, that is to ſay, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> came the reſurrection. As in <hi>Adam</hi> wee dye, ſo in Chriſt we riſe againe. The fall of <hi>Adam</hi> was of power to bring in death, ſhall not the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſt be able to deſerue the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againe to life?</p>
                  <p>Chriſt in his glorious reſurrection hath ſhewed himſelfe the conquerour of all his enemies, therefore alſo of death, which alſo at length hee ſhall altogether aboliſh. Chriſt is an eternall King, therefore he ſhall raiſe the citizens of his
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150476:62"/> kingdome from death, that they may liue with him for euer. Chriſt hath fréed not onely our ſoule, but alſo our body from the yoake of ſinne, and hath ordained it to the inheritan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of eternall life, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be raiſed out of the duſt, that it may enter into the poſſeſſion of this life, deſerued for it of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Out of all which it euidently appeares,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theodor. in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>tom.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 77. 1 Cor. 3.16</note> that Chriſt is the ſuretie and pledge of our reſurrection: furthermore, our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are the temples and houſes of the holy Ghoſt, hee will not ſuffer this his Temple to lye hidden in the duſt and aſhes, but will build it vp againe, and make it a great deale more glorious then it was in this life.<note place="margin">Hagg. 2.4.</note> Euen as the latter temple at Hieruſalem had a greater glory then the former.<note place="margin">1 Reg 6.32.</note> In <hi>Salomons</hi> temple there were incorruptible palmes, ſo the bodies of the godly ſhall not be ſubiect to eternall corruption, ſéeing they are the habitations of the eternall ſpirit.<note place="margin">Iren. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>34.</hi>
                     </note> This alſo is ſomewhat that our bodies are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by the body and bloud of Chriſt, in the wholeſome vſe of the holy ſupper, how therefore ſhall they remaine in the graue? how ſhall the fleſh bee ſayd to come into corruption, and not to taſte of life, which is nouriſhed with the body and bloud of the Lord? Euen as the bread which is of the earth, after the word is added to it, is now no common bread, but the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, conſiſting of two things, an earthly and an heauenly: ſo our bodies receiuing the Euchariſt, are not now
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:150476:63"/> corruptible, hauing the hope of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.54.</note>Surely, the fleſh of CHRIST is quickening food, therefore hee which eateth this fleſh hath eternall life, and Chriſt will raiſe him againe in the laſt day.<note place="margin">Lactan. lib. <hi>4.</hi> inſtitut. cap. <hi>48.</hi>
                     </note> Adde that the ſoule in this life by the body and with the body doth worke eyther good or euill, ſéeing it is put into the body, therefore the iuſtice of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that thoſe which were ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the worke, be ioyned together in the reward, thoſe that are ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the fault, be ioyned together in the puniſhment. Therefore all of vs ſhall appeare before the iudgement ſeat of CHRIST,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10. <hi>Tertul. in Apol. c.</hi> 45. <hi>p.</hi> 337.</note> that euery one may receiue thoſe things which he hath done in his body, whether they be good or euill. The ſoules haue not deſerued without the fleſh, in which they haue done all things: finally, to theſe vnmoueable props of Arguments may be added the examples of thoſe that haue béene raiſed vp againe, whom Chriſt by his owne, the Prophets and Apoſtles by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of GOD haue called backe to life,<note place="margin">Tertul. de reſurrect. p. <hi>44.</hi> Lactan. <hi>6.</hi> dico. inſtitu. cap. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> for teſtimonie of the future reſurrection, which theſe partakers of immortalitie and eternitie doe exhibite vnto vs which are ioyned vnto them in faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:150476:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIIII.</hi> The abſurditie of the Reſurrection.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>THe article of the Reſurrection of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies doth moſt ſtrongly oppoſe nature and humane reaſon, from whence alſo the hope of the reſurrection is ſometimes not a little weakened in my heart by the ſtormes of diuers cogitations.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>THE foundations of our faith are the oracles of the holy Ghoſt, not the predicaments of our owne reaſon. We beléeue the reſurrection of the dead, vnder the obedience of this faith wee ought to captiuate all our reaſon.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.5.</note> GOD can doe aboue all things ſuperabundantly more then wee aſke or vnderſtand. Thinke therefore on him that promiſeth, and thou ſhalt haue him to performe whatſoeuer things GOD ſayth, they are not words, but workes. Let vs graunt that GOD can doe ſomething,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.20 Phil. <hi>lib. de decal. p.</hi> 477 <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>Bern ſer.</hi> 4. <hi>de nat. col.</hi> 43. 1 Cor. 15.37</note> which wee may confeſſe that wee cannot finde out, in ſuch things all the reaſon of the deed is the power of the ſpeaker. It will be an eaſie matter for him, by whom the mother her ſelfe hath not loſt the corruption of fleſh by bringing forth, that this corruptible alſo may put on incorrution by riſing againe. It is ſomewhat alſo that in nature her ſelfe diuers repreſentations of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are ſet forth vnto vs.</p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:150476:64"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 38.</note>That which thou ſoweſt is not quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, vnleſſe it firſt dye: and what ſoweſt thou,<note place="margin">Verſ. 39.</note> not the body that ſhall be, but bare Corne, that is to ſay, of Wheate, or of ſome other.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de verb. Apoſt. ſerm. <hi>34.</hi>
                     </note> But God giueth to it a body after his owne pleaſure, and to euery ſéed his owne body. He therefore which quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens the dead and putrified graines of ſéeds, by which thou mayeſt liue in this world, will much more raiſe vp thine owne ſelfe, that thou mayeſt liue for euer. The light that daily dies ſhines forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note place="margin">Tertul. in Apol. c. <hi>45.</hi> p. <hi>73</hi> &amp;c.</note> and the darkneſſe by euen turnes departing, doth returne: the ſtarres that are put out beginne againe to liue: the times beginne where they are ended; the fruits are conſumed and doe returne; ſurely the ſéedes vnleſſe they be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and diſſolued, doe not ariſe ſo fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: all things are ſaued by periſhing, all things are reformed from death. The day dies into the night,<note place="margin">Id lib. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrect. car. pag. <hi>54.</hi>
                     </note> and is buried round about with darkeneſſe, the honour of the World is polluted and all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof is made blacke. All things are foule, ſilent, and amazed: euery where there is a vacation, and reſt of things: ſo the light that is loſt is mourned for. And yet againe with her attire, with her grace, with the Sunne, the ſame both ſound and whole doth begin to be renued to the whole world, killing her death, the night: opening her graue, the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: being heire to her ſelfe, vntill the night alſo be renued againe, ſhe likewiſe with her attire. For the beames of the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:150476:64"/> ſtarres alſo are againe made to flame, whom the mornings light had extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. The abſence alſo of the conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is brought backe, which the deſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of times had taken away. The mirrours alſo of the Moone are trimd a new, which the number of the dayes of the moneth had worne out. The Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Sommers, the Springs, and the Autumnes returne in their ſeaſon, with their owne ſtrength, manners, fruits, yea the earth is taught of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to cloathe Trées, after they are made naked, to giue freſh and new tinctures to the Flowres, to giue the hearbs againe, to bring in the ſame ſéedes which are conſumed, and not to bring them in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are conſumed.</p>
                  <p>A wonderfull matter! Of a deceiuer ſhée is become a ſauer: ſhée ſnatcheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that ſhe may reſtore: ſhée deſtroyes that ſhee may kéepe: ſhée corrupts that ſhée may make whole: ſhée firſt lauiſhly conſumes that afterward ſhée may make it more. Surely, ſhée reſtores things more plentifull and more faire, then thoſe ſhée did conſume. Of a truth, I may ſay at once, the condition of all things is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored againe by death, which is increaſe, and iniurie which is Vſury, and loſſe which is gaine. Whatſoeuer thou mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with now, hath béene, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou ſhalt léeſe, there is nothing but it ſhall be againe. All things returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſtate, when they ſhall depart. Therefore are they brought to an end
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:150476:65"/> that they may be new made. Nothing periſheth but that it may be ſaued. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this whole order of things which is in reuolution, is a witneſſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead. God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed it in his workes before he wrote it in letters: hée hath preached it by his ſtrength, before he vttered it in words. Hée ſent Nature before to be thy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, meaning to ſend Prophecie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: that ſo much the more eaſily thou mayeſt beléeue Prophecie, being the Scholler of Nature: that thou mayeſt by and by entertaine when thou heareſt, that which euery where thou now ſéeſt: and not doubt but that GOD will be a raiſer againe of thy fleſh,<note place="margin">All this <hi>Tertull.</hi>
                     </note> which knoweſt him to be the reſtorer of all things. Are ſuch lypes as theſe to be thought to be ſet out in vaine in the whole ſtate of things? Is GOD to be iudged weaker then Nature? Nay, looke vpon thy ſelfe, and know a teſtimonie of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">Id in Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo. aduer. gentes. c. <hi>45.</hi> p. <hi>737.</hi>
                     </note> Remember what thou wert, before thou waſt, ſurely nothing: for thou mighteſt haue remembred it if thou hadſt béene any thing. Thou there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which waſt nothing before thou hadſt thy being: being made nothing, when thou ſhalt ceaſe to be, why canſt thou not be againe of nothing by the wil of the ſame founder, which would haue thée to be of nothing? What new thing ſhall happen vnto thée? thou which wert not, wert made: when againe thou ſhalt not be, thou ſhalt be made: Render a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:150476:65"/> if thou canſt, which way thou wert made: and then ſhalt thou demand, which way thou ſhalt be made: and yet more eaſily ſhalt thou be made that which ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time thou haſt béene, which wert not hardly made, that which neuer thou hadſt béene.<note place="margin">Id de reſur. carnis p. <hi>54.</hi>
                     </note> If God hath made all things out of nothing, he can againe frame the fleſh brought to nothing, out of nothing. Surely hée is fit to reſtore which hath made, how much more is it to haue made, then to haue reſtored; to haue giuen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning then to haue new framed, ſo thou mayeſt beléeue that the reſtoring of thy fleſh is eaſier then the firſt making therof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLV.</hi> The flames of Purgatorie.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Feare the puniſhing flames of the fire of Purgatorie after death;<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.3.</note> for ſeeing I am compaſt about with diuers infirmities of ſinnes, I feare leaſt God ſhould therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with me into his iudgement, and moſt iuſtly adiudge me to the flames of Purgatory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>THoſe with whom God doth enter into iudgement, that is, which are not in this life reconciled to God, thoſe doth he not adiudge to the fire of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, there to be tormented for a certaine finite time, but to the infernall and not to be quenched fire, there to be broiled for all eternitie. But they which doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their ſinnes ſeriouſly, and beléeue truly on Chriſt, they haue the hand-writing of Chriſt their Sauiour,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:150476:66"/> that they néed to feare no place of ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row and torments after death, for ſo hée ſayth:<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.24</note> 
                     <hi>Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you, hee which heareth my word, and beleeueth him which hath ſent mee, hath life eternall, and commeth not into iudgement, but hath paſt from death to life.</hi> The tables of truth doe acknowledge two rankes of men onely, that is to ſay, the good and the bad, the penitent and the impenitent, the beléeuing and the vnbeléeuing: two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles onely after death,<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> hypog. Id ſer. <hi>8.</hi> de verb. Apoſt. Id. <hi>21.</hi> de ciuit. Dei. cap. <hi>25.</hi> Id. <hi>1.</hi> de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. merit. &amp; remiſ. cap. <hi>28.</hi>
                     </note> that is to ſay, of conſolation and torment, of reward and payne, of Heauen and Hell: We are vtterly ignorant of, neither doe we finde in the Scriptures, a third kinde of men and places: there are but two dwellings, one in the kingdome euerlaſting, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the euerlaſting fire: therefore is not any place in the midſt of theſe for any where hee may not be in puniſhment, which ſhall not be placed in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that hee cannot chuſe but be with the Deuill, which is not with Chriſt. <hi>Hee that ſhall beleeue,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 16.16</note> ſayth CHRIST, <hi>and be baptized, ſhall be ſaued, but hee that doth not beleeue, ſhall be condemned. Hee that beleeueth in the Sonne is not iudged,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.18.</note> 
                     <hi>but hee that doth not beleeue is iudged already, becauſe he doth not beleeue on the name of the onely begotten Sonne of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">verſ. 36.</note> 
                     <hi>He that beleeueth on the Sonne hath eternall life, but hee that doth not beleeue on the Sonne ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines vpon him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 5 29</note> 
                     <hi>They that haue done good, ſhall come forth to the reſurrection of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:150476:66"/> life, but they that haue done euill to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of iudgement.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 25.46</note> 
                     <hi>The bleſſed ſhall goe into euerlaſting life, and the curſed into euerlaſting fire.</hi> And that this immediate ſeparation of the godly and vngodly is to be made not onely in the laſt day, but alſo by and by after death, the example of the rich glutton doth teach vs,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.23</note> whoſe ſoule is thruſt into Hell, and of the godly <hi>Lazarus,</hi> whoſe ſoule is tranſlated of the Angels into Paradiſe: the example of the conuerted Théefe doth teach vs,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.43</note> to whom Chriſt promiſeth the ingreſſe into Paradiſe, on that very day wherein hée was to dye:<note place="margin">Apoc. 14.13.</note> the ſpirit of Trueth doth teach vs, pronouncing them henceforth bleſſed that dye in the Lord. There is none other purgation or expiation of ſinnes, then in the bloud of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.7. Eſa. 53.5. Rom. 5.1. 1 Iohn 3.14. Sap. 4.1.</note> which waſheth vs altogether from all our ſins, the chaſtiſement of our peace is vpon him, that he might be peace to vs: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he which beléeues on him is iuſtified, and hath peace with God, is tranſlated from death to life, neither néed hee feare any torment after death.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXVI.</hi> The rigour of the laſt iudgement.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Tempted.</head>
                  <p>I Feare the rigour and terrour of the laſt iudgement. Aboue mee will be the ſeuere iudge, beneath mee gaping Hell, within mee my Conſcience gnawing, without me fire burning, on my right hand my ſins accuſing
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:150476:67"/> me, on my left hand the Diuels terrifying me, round about mee the good Angels dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mee to hell, and the euill drawing mee to the ſame. Satan will accuſe me, my ſinnes will accuſe mee,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bern.</hi> in Rithm.</note> my conſcience will accuſe me. I feare much the countenance of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere Iudge, from whom nothing that is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſhall be kept cloſe, neither ſhall any thing remaine vnreuenged. No man ſhall be able to eſcape his power, to deceiue his wiſedome, to turne his equitie, or to reuoke his iudgement.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Comforter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF thou beleeueſt on the Sonne, thou ſhalt not be iudged,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.18.</note> that is to ſay, <hi>with that ſeuere and condemning rigour of iudgement. If thou heareſt the word of Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.24.</note> 
                     <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueſt him, thou commeſt not into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thy cauſe ſhall not be diſcuſt in that rigorous examination of iudgement,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1.10. Auguſt <hi>in Pſa.</hi> 100.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeeing Chriſt hath freed all that beleeue on him, from the wrath to come:</hi> Truly the day of iudgement is to be feared of the wicked for the puniſhment, but is to be loued of the good for the crowne: to them it ſhall be a day of grace, and of large remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.<note place="margin">Luk. 21.28</note> 
                     <hi>Lift vp your heads,</hi> ſaith the Son, <hi>and know that your redemption draweth neere.</hi> The Bride doth not feare the comming of her Bridegroome, now thy ſoule is eſpouſed to Chriſt by faith, hée will appeare in the day of iudgement to that end,<note place="margin">Apoc. 197</note> that hée may bring her in as it were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is Bride to the heauenly marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, what place therefore can there be
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:150476:67"/> here for terrour or feare? That day ſhall be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> day of deliuerance, becauſe it ſhall frée vs altogether from the wretched cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of ſinne and death. Into the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſeruice of Chriſt, it is the day of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, becauſe it ſhall plucke vs away from all the heape of euils, and waight of calamities: it is the day of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, becauſe it ſhall redéeme vs wholly from that continuall wraſtling of the fleſh, and perillous warfare. It is the day of refreſhing, becauſe it ſhall ſet vs thirſtie and out of breath, into a place of reſt, by the fountaine of liuing water, from the heate of calamities.<note place="margin">Act 3.20. Apoc. 22.2</note> Therefore let our Bridegroome Chriſt come, let him come, whatſoeuer ſoule is the true Spouſe of Chriſt, ſealed by the earneſt of the ſpirit, led by the loue of Chriſt, let her ſay, <hi>Come Lord Ieſu.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>in Pſa.</hi> 147.</note> If wée loue Chriſt truly, ſurely wée alſo deſire his comming, for it is a peruerſe thing to feare leaſt he come whom thou loueſt: to pray, <hi>let thy Kingdome come,</hi> and to feare leaſt thou be heard. But from whence is the feare? becauſe hée is to come a Iudge? What is hée vniuſt? doth hée beare vs ill-will? is he enuious? doth he expect to know thy cauſe from another, leaſt perhaps he whom thou haſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, either deceiue thée by colluſion, or failing in leſſer elequence or abilitie, be not able in words to ſhew the goodneſſe of thine innocencie? None of theſe. Who therefore is to come? Wherefore doeſt thou not reioyce? Who is to come to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150476:68"/> iudge thée, but he which came to be iudged for thee? Feare not the accuſer, of whom he hath ſaid, the Prince of this world is caſt forth. Feare not an euill Aduocate, for he will be thine Aduocate, which ſhall be thy Iudge. He will be both thy ſelfe, and thy cauſe. The word of thy cauſe, the teſtimonie of thy Conſcience.<note place="margin">All this of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                     </note> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer therefore thou be that feareſt the Iudge to come, correct now thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. There is no cauſe therefore why thou ſhouldeſt feare the Iudge to come. He ſhal be thy Iudge, which alſo is thine Aduocate. He ſhall be thy Iudge, which hath giuen a promiſe to his Saints, that by his teſtimonie and example they are to iudge the world. He ſhall be thy Iudge, in whom from euerlaſting thou wert choſen to life. Hée ſhall be thy Iudge, which was thy King, how ſhall a King deſtroy his owne people? He ſhall be thy Iudge, whoſe true member thou art by faith, how ſhall the head deſtroy his members?<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33</note> Who ſhall accuſe the choſen of God? It is God which iuſtifies, who ſhall condemne? It is Chriſt which is dead, nay which is riſen againe, which is at the right hand of God, and makes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for vs, how ſhall hée deſtroy thoſe whom he hath taken into his tuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for whom, leaſt they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.16.</note> he came into the world? <hi>Chriſt ſhall iudge according to the Goſpell, but now the beleeuers haue not deſpiſed it, but receiued it with true faith.</hi> They haue heard the voice of Chriſt inuiting them
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150476:68"/> to conuerſion;<note place="margin">Matth. 11.28.</note> 
                     <hi>Come vnto me all yee which labour and are heauie loaden, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh you:</hi> therefore they ſhall alſo heare his voice inuiting them to the heauenly poſſeſſion. <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 25.34.</note> 
                     <hi>receiue the inheritance of the Kingdome of heauen, which was prepared for you from the beginning.</hi> He ſhall be the Iudge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſe face goe grace and truth, grace hath aboliſht the ſinnes of the beléeuers, truth hath giuen vnto them the promiſes of eternall life. Neither is there any cauſe, that thou feare the horrible vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall deſtruction of heauen and earth. <hi>Heauen and earth ſhall paſſe away,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 21.33 Eſa 40.8.</note> 
                     <hi>but the words of Chriſt ſhall not paſſe away. The word of the Lord abides for euer, if thou ſticke to this word with true faith, thou like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhalt abide for euer.</hi> Thou haſt loſt nothing, where by inordinate loue thou haſt poſſeſſed nothing, thy treaſure is not the riches of this world, but the delight of the heauenly Kingdome: let the world be on fire, it is ſufficient for thée that Chriſt thy treaſure liueth. Let the frame of heauen and earth periſh, flie, paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, thou haſt moſt faithfull promiſes of a new heauen, and a new earth.<note place="margin">Eſa. 65.17. 2 Pet. 3.12 Apoc. 21.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I create a new heauen and a new earth,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>in which ſhall dwell righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſo that no man remembreth the former things any more.</hi> Let the lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of thy pilgrimage fall downe, the euerlaſting houſe of the heauenly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey doth abide. Neither is there any cauſe, why thou feare the accuſation ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:150476:69"/> of Satan or of the Law, or of thine owne ſinnes; thy ſinnes are caſt into the depth of the Sea, ſuppoſe into the bottomleſſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t of Gods mercy.<note place="margin">Mich. 7.19 Eſ. 38.17. Eze. 18.24. Pſa. 32.1. Pſal. 51.1.</note> GOD hath caſt them behinde his backe, ſo that hée will not remember them hereafter. Beléeue, Satan ſhall not draw vp thoſe ſinnes out of the Sea, nor dare to bring them into the ſight of the Iudge. Thy ſinnes are forgiuen, they are couered, they are blotted out, they ſhall not be brought againe into iudgement. The accuſation drawne againſt the godly, of the Diuell, ſhall be vaine, becauſe the blotting out of the hand-writing made by the bloud of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.14</note> ſhall be turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. The accuſation of ſinne ſhall be vaine, becauſe the pardon giuen by Chriſt ſhall be turned againſt it. The accuſation of the Law ſhall be vaine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe reconciliation with God through faith hath gone before in this life. To conclude, there is no cauſe that thou feare the ſodaine returne of Chriſt to iudgement, for although the day of the Lord ſhal come as a Thiefe in the night,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.2.</note> yet God hath not appointed vs to wrath, but that wée may attaine ſaluation through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> which hath dyed for vs, that whether we wake or ſléepe, we may alwaies liue with him. The day of iudgement is not to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them for whom the Kingdome of heauen was prepared from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.34. Eph. 1.4.</note> which were choſen in Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the foundations of the earth were
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:150476:69"/> laid. Commend therefore into the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hands of God, the pretious pledge of thy ſoule, he will keepe it in death and iudgement, and he will bring it vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the body into the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the heauenly Court, to euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:70"/>
            <head>A PRAYER <hi>in Sickneſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eare mee, O God, giuer and reſtorer of life, in whoſe hands is life and death, health and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Heare mee, not according to the deſire of my will, but according to the good pleaſure of thy will. If thou wilt thou canſt make mee whole; ſay but one word onely, and I ſhall be whole; thou art the length of my dayes, in thy hands are my lots; but if thou now calleſt me by the way of Death to the heauenly Countrey, mortifie firſt in mee all inordinate loue of this life; giue me the ſtrength of the ſpirit, that I may ouercome the ſorrowes of death, and in the midſt of the darkneſſe of mine eyes, when they waxe dimme, kindle and encreaſe in me the light
<pb facs="tcp:150476:70"/> of heart, with thee is the fountaine of true life, and in thy light I ſhall ſee light. Thy death, O good Ieſus, is the medicine of my death, and the merit of eternall life. I embrace thy vvord vvith a faithfull heart, therefore I am ſure that thou dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt by faith in my heart, I will not let thee depart out of my heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou bleſſe me, and lift me vp with quickning conſolation. Thou haſt ſaid, He that beleeueth on mee ſhall not die for euer; this word my heart doth ſet before thee, and in this faith I draw neere to the throne of grace, thou wilt not correct nor put back him that comes vnto thee. Let thy pretious bloud vvaſh mee from my ſinnes, let thy wounds hide mee from the wrath of God and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of iudgement, I wil die in thee, thou ſhalt liue in mee; I will abide in thee, and thou ſhalt abide in me; thou wilt not leaue me in death and duſt, but wilt raiſe me vp to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of life. Thou haſt fought and ouercome for mee, now fight and ouercome in me, let thy ſtrength be performed in mine infirmitie:
<pb facs="tcp:150476:71"/> My ſoule cleaues vnto thee, I will not ſuffer my ſelfe to be pluckt away from thee, let thy peace, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all vnderſtanding, keepe my heart and ſenſes. Into thy hands I commend my ſpirit, thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed me thou God of truth, take vp the poore ſoule, which thou haſt created, which thou haſt redeemed, which thou haſt waſhed from ſins with thy bloud, which thou haſt ſealed with the earneſt of the holy Ghoſt, which thou haſt fed with thy body &amp; bloud; It is thine, thou haſt giuen it vnto mee, take vp that which thine is, and remit the guilt of my ſinnes wherewith I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed it. Let not the fruit of thy Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion periſh in me, let not thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud waxe barren in me. In thee O Lord haue I hoped, let me not be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:71"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:72"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150476:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
